<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>Plant stress—new perspectives on an old
concept</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Aphalo</surname>
<given-names>Pedro J.</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Pedro J. Aphalo</string-name>

<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sadras</surname>
<given-names>Víctor O.</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Víctor O. Sadras</string-name>

<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jansen</surname>
<given-names>Marcel A. K.</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Marcel A. K. Jansen</string-name>

<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">c</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Helsinki, Department of Agricultural
Sciences</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>South Australia Research and Development
Institute</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University College Cork</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1"></corresp>
</author-notes>









<history></history>






</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>“Definitions and terminology are crucially important. A large part
  of the fruitfulness of scientific thought has come from one simple
  fact. It is that hitherto every scientific term has had an exact
  definition, verbal or mathematical, universally accepted.”
  (<xref alt="Pye 1995" rid="ref-Pye1995" ref-type="bibr">Pye
  1995</xref>). Contrary to the quotation above, the terms “stress” and
  “limitation” as used in the plant sciences do not have exact
  definitions universally accepted and unambiguously recognizable.</p>
  <p>Because science often deals with unfamiliar objects and phenomena
  like genes, black holes and quantum entanglement, we can either (i)
  create a wholly new vocabulary or (ii) capture the apparent
  similarities between established concepts and terms in the “source
  domain” and reason analogically to transfer these onto a novel
  setting, the “target domain”; this is how scientific metaphors are
  constructed
  (<xref alt="Reynolds 2022" rid="ref-Reynolds2022" ref-type="bibr">Reynolds
  2022</xref>). Physics is the source domain of the term “stress” that
  has been transferred to several target domains including biology in
  what Palma
  (<xref alt="2016" rid="ref-Palma2016" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>)
  calls an epistemic metaphor. Epistemic metaphors when incorporated
  into the scientific vocabulary lose the duality of meaning ordinary
  metaphors have and their meaning in scientific writing and speech
  becomes unambiguously defined by the context in which they are used.
  However, the many meanings of “stress” in Biology seem to fail this
  test, and ambiguity of meaning has become an obstacle to communication
  and understanding
  (<xref alt="Jansen and Potters 2017" rid="ref-Jansen2017" ref-type="bibr">Jansen
  and Potters 2017</xref>).</p>
  <p>As biological systems are far more complex than physical systems
  (<xref alt="Kauffman2019?" rid="ref-Kauffman2019" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Kauffman2019?</bold></xref>;
  <xref alt="Kauffman and Roli 2023" rid="ref-Kauffman2023" ref-type="bibr">Kauffman
  and Roli 2023</xref>), multiple alternative mappings of concepts from
  physics to this new domain are possible. A key difference compared to
  mechanics is that biological systems are hierarchically organized and
  can be studied at different levels of organization from individual
  cells and their organelles to biomes
  (<xref alt="Capra and Luisi 2014" rid="ref-Capra2014" ref-type="bibr">Capra
  and Luisi 2014</xref>). In practice, stress definitions are based on
  the lack of fulfilment of a condition. However, the condition and,
  consequently, also the criteria used to assess lack of its fulfilment
  varies depending on the aims of the research or activity at hand
  (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
  Thus, the meaning of the term “stress”as applied to plants can remain
  ambiguous. To a smaller degree the same problem also affects the
  related concept of “limitation”.</p>
  <p>Levine
  (<xref alt="1985" rid="ref-Levine1985" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>)
  wrote “My chapter defines the concept of stress. I am not certain
  whether one who undertakes this task either has an enormous ego, is
  immeasurably stupid, or is totally mad.” In a more positive tone,
  Grubb
  (<xref alt="1992" rid="ref-Grubb1992" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>) in
  his presidential address on ecological theory tells `What I mean to
  indicate through the first part of my title, — ‘a positive distrust in
  simplicity’ — is that I not only distrust the simplest kinds of
  generalization, but also believe strongly that we must not simply
  dismiss them when they are proved wanting. Instead we must respond
  positively — we must be prepared to seek generalizations that are less
  simple and more likely to reflect the real world.’</p>
  <p>We, a physiologist (MAKJ), an ecologist (PJA), and an agronomist
  (VOS), review here the different meanings with which “stress” is used
  in plant sciences, and contrast these meanings with current
  physiological, ecological, and agronomic knowledge. Our aim is not to
  distil a single “true” definition of stress. Instead, we explore how
  the multiple meanings given to the term “stress” relate to each other
  and to “limitation”, “stressor” and “strain” proposing a framework
  guided by theory and observation to classify and refine them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="past-and-current-uses-of-the-term-plant-stress">
  <title>Past and current uses of the term “plant stress”</title>
  <p>The concept of stress originally used in physics to describe
  mechanical forces acting on inanimate objects was transferred to
  target domains including psychology, physiology, and medicine, and
  eventually to agronomy and ecology as a metaphor describing various
  factors and “pressures” acting on whole organisms, on their component
  parts or on assemblages of organisms. Selye
  (<xref alt="1936" rid="ref-Selye1936" ref-type="bibr">1936</xref>)
  when introducing “stress” to biology, described the development of
  stress as a process with three phases: “alarm”, “resistance” and
  “’exhaustion”, with normal function compromised only in the last of
  these phases. Years later, Selye
  (<xref alt="1975" rid="ref-Selye1975" ref-type="bibr">1975</xref>)
  introduced the concepts of “eustress” and “distress”, likely by
  adapting the terms eustress and dys-stress as used in sports by Harris
  (<xref alt="1970" rid="ref-Harris1970" ref-type="bibr">1970</xref>) to
  contrast pleasent stress and painful or unpleasent stress. According
  to Selye’s use in medicine, stress events could lead to both ulterior
  positive effects, or “eustress”, or negative effects, or “distress”.
  Selye, an endocrinologist, contended that stress triggered by
  different stressors shared the same physiological rsponses. As we will
  see below, with time, and with its use with plants the meaning of
  “stress” broadened to encompass responses that are heterogeneous in
  mechanism and levels of organization.</p>
  <p>Bidwell
  (<xref alt="1979" rid="ref-Bidwell1979" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>)
  writes a comprehensive definition as “Normal physiology is maintained
  under ideal environmental conditions. However, plants seldom exist
  under just the right conditions. Usually something is lacking; often
  several factors are far from ideal. Because of the fact of
  competition, plants often live at the limit of their capacity to
  survive one or more adverse conditions. This creates considerable
  stress on the organism, which reacts by various biochemical and
  physiological mechanisms, to overcome, avoid, or neutralize the
  stress.” Levitt
  (<xref alt="1980" rid="ref-Levitt1980" ref-type="bibr">1980</xref>)
  defined stress as: “Any environmental factor potentially unfavorable
  to living organisms.” Levitt
  (<xref alt="1980" rid="ref-Levitt1980" ref-type="bibr">1980</xref>)
  based his proposal for “stress and strain terminology” on the use of
  these terms in physics. He conceded that the term “strain” as used in
  biology had a connotation of plastic rather than elastic strain, while
  he considered both as of interest. He defined in a biological sense
  stress as “an external factor acting on an organism” and strain as “a
  physical or chemical change produced by the stress”. He also states
  that plastic strain may be reparable while elastic strain is
  reversible. He used the terms “stable adaptation” for adaptation of
  the genotype through natural selection and “unstable adaptation” for
  acclimation of the phenotype. He also equated hardiness with the
  ability to acclimate. Contemporary with Levitt, Grime
  (<xref alt="1979" rid="ref-Grime1979" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>),
  Grime
  (<xref alt="1981" rid="ref-Grime1981" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>)
  linked stress, resources and disturbances to evolution and natural
  selection in a classification of plants into competitors, stress
  tolerators and ruderals (C-S-R) based on the strategies expected to
  contribute to fitness in environments with differences in resource
  abundance. We already see multiple views: Bidwell sees stress and
  ensuing strain as the norm, Levitt sees stress as a rather exceptional
  case that may cause strain or not, and finally Grime sees stress as a
  persistent condition in the environment that filters species but does
  not strain those species that pass the filter.</p>
  <p>From the late 1980s to early 2000s, the concept of stress evolved
  concurrently in different biological fields and geographies. North
  American ecologists emphasized that simultaneous exposure to multiple
  stressors and limiting factors is the most common case in nature,
  contrasting this observation to the frequently used simplified
  experimental settings focusing on individual factors (e.g.,
  <xref alt="Chapin et al. 1987" rid="ref-Chapin1987" ref-type="bibr">Chapin
  et al. 1987</xref>). Winner
  (<xref alt="1991" rid="ref-Mooney1991" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>)
  wrote “The term ‘stressor’ can suggest that stress is caused by a
  single variable, however in the natural environment this is rarely the
  case.” In this view, “stress” comprises the states of multiple
  environmental factors interacting with a realized phenotype, and each
  of these states can potentially induce multiple strains in plants.
  (<xref alt="BrayXXXX?" rid="ref-BrayXXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>BrayXXXX?</bold></xref>)
  referred to stresses as external conditions that “…adversely affect
  growth, development or productivity”, thus recognizing three possible
  criteria for diagnosis. Packham et al.
  (<xref alt="1992" rid="ref-Packham1992" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>)
  instead, focusing on biomass as the criterion used, stated that
  “’Stress’, as it applies to plants, can be defined as the external
  constraints which limit the rate of dry matter production of all or
  part of the vegetation […]. ‘Disturbance’ may be regarded as
  consisting of the mechanisms which limit the plant biomass by causing
  its partial or total destruction.” In Europe, the frequently “loose”
  use for the term “stress” prompted Lichtenthaler
  (<xref alt="1998" rid="ref-Lichtenthaler1998" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>)
  to propose a criterion to distinguish between stress and normal
  responses at the physiological level, stated as: “Despite their
  capacity for fast acclimation of metabolic fluxes and specific
  adaptations as well as the development of certain stress tolerance
  mechanisms, plants are often exposed to sudden short-term or long-term
  stress events that eventually reduce cell activity and plant growth to
  a minimum. This can lead to severe damage ultimately causing cell
  death if the stress coping mechanisms or repair mechanisms of plants
  are overworked.” He recognized four phases: “response phase” or alarm
  reaction (beginning of stress), “restitution phase” or stage of
  resistance (continuing stress), “end phase” or stage of exhaustion
  (long-term stress), and “regeneration phase” or partial or full
  regeneration of the physiological function, when the stressor is
  removed.
  (<xref alt="Koerner1999?" rid="ref-Koerner1999" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Koerner1999?</bold></xref>)
  challenged the frequent use of the terms stress, constraints, and
  limitation to describe environments with low primary production such
  alpine ecosystems, describing the situation as “a widespread
  misconception in functional ecology” arguing that the species that
  inhabit these ecosystems are adapted to such conditions. Based on the
  idea of stress as a filter, Körner
  (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-Koerner2003" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>)
  concluded that “Stressful environments hardly exist” in nature, as the
  species that pass the “filter” can be expected to thrive. In a nuanced
  view of interactions, Gutschick and BassiriRad
  (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-Gutschick2003" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>)
  concluded that the co-occurrence of low temperature and high light
  intensity that leads to photoinhibition in leaves of Eucalyptus
  pauciflora is not a case of multiple stresses, as “neither the high
  light nor the subfreezing temperatures are themselves very adverse for
  the plant”. The recognition that fluctuations in resource availability
  lead to recurring temporal dynamics in plant interactions
  (<xref alt="Goldberg and Novoplansky 1997" rid="ref-Goldberg1997" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg
  and Novoplansky 1997</xref>), the relevance of ecological and
  evolutionary theory to agricultural systems
  (<xref alt="Martı'nez-Ghersa, Ghersa, and Satorre 2000" rid="ref-MartinezGhersa2000" ref-type="bibr">Martı'nez-Ghersa,
  Ghersa, and Satorre 2000</xref>; reviewed by
  <xref alt="Denison 2012" rid="ref-Denison2012" ref-type="bibr">Denison
  2012</xref>) and the role of non-cognitive sensory-based, i. e.,
  information-based responses and communication in plant interactions
  (<xref alt="Aphalo and Ballaré 1995" rid="ref-Aphalo1995" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
  and Ballaré 1995</xref>;
  <xref alt="Novoplanskyxxxx?" rid="ref-Novoplanskyxxxx" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Novoplanskyxxxx?</bold></xref>;
  <xref alt="Callaway 2002" rid="ref-Callaway2002" ref-type="bibr">Callaway
  2002</xref>) were described. Even if new ideas and criteria were
  formulated during this period, the three contrasting views from the
  1970’s and 1980’s remained.</p>
  <p>The next two decades saw significant changes in ecological theory
  as a result of methodological developments that allowed or forced a
  revised view of evolution and inheritance and the role of plasticity
  in fitness. Schulze, Beck, and Müller-Hohenstein
  (<xref alt="2005" rid="ref-Schulze2005" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>)
  focused on the individual plant, defining “stress reactions” as
  deviations from the “physiological normal type”, that of plants
  growing under optimal quantities or intensities of factors and
  influences and thus “maximizing physiologically achievable
  performance”. They recognize, however, that plants almost never find
  such conditions. They also state that “growth is only one of many
  reactions of a plant to its environment.”
  (<xref alt="Fedoroff2010?" rid="ref-Fedoroff2010" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Fedoroff2010?</bold></xref>)
  discussed a systems view of the stress response in relation to
  stomatal guard cells. Her analysis connects responses of guard cells
  to knowledge on signals, structure, and function at levels of
  organization below whole cells while Kranner et al.
  (<xref alt="2010" rid="ref-Kranner2010" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>)
  recognized that stress can simultaneously trigger multiple strains in
  plants and that these strains can be chained. Thus, the hierarchical
  structure and systems views are incorporated, but with a strong focus
  of the individual plant as the target of stress.</p>
  <p>More recently, Taiz et al.
  (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-Taiz2015" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) with
  a focus on physiology define stress as “any environmental condition
  that prevents the plant from achieving its full genetic potential.”
  with genetic potential defined as the maximum growth and reproductive
  potential based on biomass and seed number. This simple text-book
  definition highlights that stress in a very broad sense, encompasses
  all conditions in the abiotic and biotic environment of a plant that
  limit its growth and/or reproduction. Keddy
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-Keddy2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)
  reviews in his textbook the concept of “stress” from an ecological
  perspective, initially using a simple definition: ‘We will use the
  word stress to describe “any environmental condition that reduces the
  rate of production of biomass”’ but later in the book, Keddy
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-Keddy2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) in
  pp. 400-402 provides a more elaborate alternative: “When thinking
  about stress, it is important to separate short-term physiological
  effects from long-term evolutionary effects.” He also considers the
  evolution of risk aversion and the role of competition. Although
  stress is usually considered as negative, there are alternative views,
  more common in discussions of stress in animals and humans, that
  consider some stress conditions as positive (eustress) (see above) or
  even a requirement for normal development
  (<xref alt="Badyaev et al. 2015" rid="ref-Badyaev2015" ref-type="bibr">Badyaev
  et al. 2015</xref>, and refs. therein).</p>
  <p>Although hardening of seedlings before out-planting, priming of
  seeds and other similar management procedures based on intentional
  exposure to conditions unfavourable for growth have been in use since
  XXXXX times by plant growers, they have had little influence on how
  plant stress has been defined in physiology and ecology. At this point
  in time, although awareness about the complexity of biological systems
  had improved and the importance of the hierarchical organization of
  ecosystems in their function had been widely accepted, contrasting
  definitions of “stress” persisted,</p>
  <p>Nowadays, on one hand, stress responses are seen as triggered by
  environmental conditions that are exceptional, unusual, or more
  generally, difficult to predict. On the other hand, “stress” is also
  used to describe conditions which can potentially cause strain, even
  in the absence of strain.</p>
  <p>The use of conflicting criteria for normality persists to our day.
  The “normal” condition is sometimes taken as the potential performance
  of the same genotype under “optimal” growth conditions, while in other
  cases it is the performance of a genotype “optimally adapted” to the
  current environment. Although rarely explicitly mentioned, this
  dichotomy creates two drastically different views about stress and
  strain. Thus, there is a need to distinguish between utilitarian (or
  practical and commercial), physiological and ecological definitions of
  stress
  (<xref alt="Körner 2018" rid="ref-Koerner2018" ref-type="bibr">Körner
  2018</xref>). According to Körner
  (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-Koerner2003" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>),
  “Biomass production, irrespective of the species involved, is almost
  always limited by one or several resources or stressors, but the suite
  of taxa present in a given space and time is not. This distinction,
  between the physiological- (process) or agronomic- (yield-) oriented
  meanings of limitation and stress, and the biodiversity-oriented
  dimension of those terms, is crucial.”</p>
  <p>Statements indicating that stress is pervasive in nature and that
  plants’ growth is nearly always limited bv strain caused by
  environmental factors (e.g.,
  <xref alt="Schulze, Beck, and Müller-Hohenstein 2005" rid="ref-Schulze2005" ref-type="bibr">Schulze,
  Beck, and Müller-Hohenstein 2005</xref>), raise questions about how
  meaningful it is to consider growth under optimal conditions as the
  “normal” reference. On the other hand, the statement that “Stressful
  environments hardly exist”
  (<xref alt="Körner 2003" rid="ref-Koerner2003" ref-type="bibr">Körner
  2003</xref>) raises questions about the levels of organization at
  which stress is usefully defined and whether the constrains that cause
  strain at one level of organization impose or not constraints at
  higher levels of organization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-changing-scientific-context">
  <title>The changing scientific context</title>
  <p>Gradually, the purely genetic-based view of evolution
  (<xref alt="Fisher 1958" rid="ref-Fisher1958" ref-type="bibr">Fisher
  1958</xref>) has been expanded to encompass other information transfer
  mechanisms under the name of extended heredity
  (<xref alt="Bonduriansky and Day 2020" rid="ref-Bonduriansky2020" ref-type="bibr">Bonduriansky
  and Day 2020</xref>). Extended heredity includes mechanisms such as
  maternal effects and transfer of epigenes, which even if usually
  persisting only for one or a few generations, are able to influence
  the outcome of natural selection, and consequently, the course of
  evolution of the genotype. Horizontal evolution
  (<xref alt="Mindell 2024" rid="ref-Mindell2024" ref-type="bibr">Mindell
  2024</xref>) recognizes that the tree-like representation of evolution
  is incomplete, proposing a network representation to accommodate
  speciation originating from hybridization and other mechanism of
  horizontal gene transfer between species.</p>
  <p>Both genotypic and environmental variation play a role in evolution
  through their effects on the fitness of individuals. However, due to
  genotypic and environmental variation, that some individuals, or even
  most individuals in a population are under strain, does not
  necessarily mean that the population as a whole is under strain or
  that its capacity for biological resilience is overwhelmed
  (<xref alt="Thorogood et al. 2023" rid="ref-Thorogood2023" ref-type="bibr">Thorogood
  et al. 2023</xref>). That living systems can be described as systems
  composed of interacting parts organized hierarchically affects how we
  should approach their study, specially when crossing
  level-of-organization boundaries (e.g.,
  <xref alt="Zeiger and Weinberg 1970" rid="ref-Zeiger1970" ref-type="bibr">Zeiger
  and Weinberg 1970</xref>;
  <xref alt="Capra and Luisi 2014" rid="ref-Capra2014" ref-type="bibr">Capra
  and Luisi 2014</xref>) so that the conclusions reached are
  biologically and practically meaningful. However, we see this
  hierarchy nowadays not as tree-like, but as a network. This is not
  only true for evolution of species, but also for trophic networks in
  ecosystems and signalling networks at the cell level. This means that
  boundaries among levels in the hierarchy can be diffuse.</p>
  <p>It is nowadays accepted that information-carrying cues and signals
  play a crucial role in the regulation of the growth and development of
  plants
  (<xref alt="H. Smith 1981" rid="ref-Smith1981" ref-type="bibr">H.
  Smith 1981</xref>;
  <xref alt="A. Novoplansky, Cohen, and Sachs 1990" rid="ref-Novoplansky1990" ref-type="bibr">A.
  Novoplansky, Cohen, and Sachs 1990</xref>;
  <xref alt="Ballaré, Scopel, and Sánchez 1990" rid="ref-Ballare1990" ref-type="bibr">Ballaré,
  Scopel, and Sánchez 1990</xref>;
  <xref alt="Aphalo and Ballaré 1995" rid="ref-Aphalo1995" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
  and Ballaré 1995</xref>;
  <xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
  and Sadras 2022</xref>). We have proposed that altered conditions
  prone to cause strain are not only dependent on the state of
  individual variables but also on spatially or temporally disrupted
  correlations among variables in the environment, because organisms
  have evolved to use such correlations as sources of information,
  including anticipation of future events or states of their environment
  (see,
  <xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
  and Sadras 2022</xref>). It has also been shown that preemptive or
  anticipatory responses by organisms, including plants, can be highly
  beneficial to fitness
  (<xref alt="Ariel Novoplansky 2016" rid="ref-Novoplansky2016" ref-type="bibr">Ariel
  Novoplansky 2016</xref>) including under exceptional “stressful”
  conditions. Importantly, such responses could be exploited when
  managing crops
  (<xref alt="Falik, Mauda, and Novoplansky 2024" rid="ref-Falik2024" ref-type="bibr">Falik,
  Mauda, and Novoplansky 2024</xref>) and in crop breeding
  (<xref alt="Boccalandro et al. 2003" rid="ref-Boccalandro2003" ref-type="bibr">Boccalandro
  et al. 2003</xref>). We now see plants as complex and actively
  regulated biological systems capable of anticipatory responses rather
  than as passive systems at the mercy of the environment
  (<xref alt="Aphalo and Ballaré 1995" rid="ref-Aphalo1995" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
  and Ballaré 1995</xref>;
  <xref alt="A. Trewavas 2014" rid="ref-Trewavas2014" ref-type="bibr">A.
  Trewavas 2014</xref>;
  <xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
  and Sadras 2022</xref>). In fact, plants “keep a memory” within and
  across generations about environmental conditions they are exposed to,
  using multiple mechanisms, allowing memories of varied persistence.
  Furthermore, communication among plants through, mostly chemical,
  signals can play a central role in the tolerance of stress and
  mitigation of strain
  (<xref alt="Falik, Mauda, and Novoplansky 2024" rid="ref-Falik2024" ref-type="bibr">Falik,
  Mauda, and Novoplansky 2024</xref>).</p>
  <p>Evolutionary mechanisms, in a broad sense, provide the ultimate
  explanation of why “stress”, in each of its definitions, is or is not
  a frequent condition in nature. From a modern perspective, how a plant
  responds to an environmental condition depends not only on the
  genotype but also on its expression in the phenotype. Crucially, from
  this perspective, responses depend on the integration of both
  information and resource availability over a long time and the
  integration of information across multiple levels of organization,
  including the sharing of information among individuals. This clashes
  with the intuitive idea that when a plant is under stress its
  responses are mainly controlled externally but when plastically
  acclimating, they are controlled internally.</p>
  <p>The definitions of stress currently in use are 30–40-year-old and
  still based on evolutionary, ecological and physiological
  understanding from those days. They have yet to incorporate the degree
  of complexity that nowadays is considered necessary for understanding
  biological systems, including plants and vegetation. The failures
  inflicted by the underlying complexity on naïve attempts of upscaling
  of physiological plant responses to higher levels of organization
  provide painful examples
  (<xref alt="Sadras 2020" rid="ref-Sadras2020" ref-type="bibr">Sadras
  2020</xref>;
  <xref alt="Thorogood et al. 2023" rid="ref-Thorogood2023" ref-type="bibr">Thorogood
  et al. 2023</xref>) showing that more of the exisiting complexity
  needs to be incorporated into “stress” theory. Below we analyse the
  relevance of these advances to the problem of plant stress, even
  asking the question of whether it is possible or not to cleanly
  distinguish acclimation from strain responses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-factors-behind-stress">
  <title>The factors behind stress</title>
  <sec id="time-and-space">
    <title>Time and space</title>
    <p>Although stress is usually considered as negative, there are
    alternative views that consider some stress conditions as positive
    (eustress) (see above), a requirement for normal development
    (<xref alt="Badyaev et al. 2015" rid="ref-Badyaev2015" ref-type="bibr">Badyaev
    et al. 2015</xref>, and refs. herein) and as useful in crop
    management
    (<xref alt="xxxx?" rid="ref-xxxx" ref-type="bibr"><bold>xxxx?</bold></xref>).
    In these cases, the assessment is done at two points in time, an
    initially negative effect (or strain) has later in the life of the
    organism a beneficial effect. Furthermore, the distinction between
    eustress and distress depends on environmental conditions at the
    time the initial stress event takes place and at the time when the
    consequences are assessed. Although this may seem like an unusual
    situation, it is very common. Anticipatory acclimation that
    contributes to tolerance of a specific future condition has in most
    cases a cost, that is detrimental if this future condition is not
    experienced, but provides a premium if it is experienced
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    Thus, if the future condition, such as rainfall, can only be
    predicted in terms of probabilities, the categorization of a plant’s
    response as stressful or beneficial is only possible in retrospect,
    when fitness or yield is assessed. More importantly, the definition
    of stress becomes time- and spatial scale dependent, as what is
    directly detrimental for one specific individual can be indirectly
    favourable for the population if it benefits other individuals
    within it concurently or at other times. Plasticity in behaviour,
    function and morphology is a necessary condition for fitness in any
    environment subject to variation
    (<xref alt="xxxx?" rid="ref-xxxx" ref-type="bibr"><bold>xxxx?</bold></xref>).
    It follows that acclimation is central to tolerance of potential
    stressors as well as for profiting from environmental “goodness”. We
    have considered that, acclimation, being a relatively slow process,
    to be effective has to be triggered by a signal or cue that precedes
    the stress event, possibly but not necessarily the potential stress
    causing variable
    (<xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>). Obviously, the slower the response, the
    earlier the plant’s response has to start.</p>
    <p>The distinction between transient vs. continuous strain is also
    relevant because a continuing strain normally has a negative
    connotation, a scenario which echoes the “exhaustion phase” in Selye
    (<xref alt="1936" rid="ref-Selye1936" ref-type="bibr">1936</xref>)
    original stress concept. However, strain refers to the
    plant-environment interaction, as continuing exposure to a potential
    stressor or stress can also result in transient strain thanks to
    acclimation in the plant overcoming it. Strain is not dichotomic, it
    varies continuously between two extremes that are rarely realized,
    at least at hierarchical levels above the individual. Thus,
    transient, decreasing and/or localized strains are likely to have
    fewer negative consequences on fitness or yield than sustained or
    increasing strains. Strain can even be considered in some cases
    positive, or even as a requirement for normal development of
    organisms
    (<xref alt="Badyaev 2005" rid="ref-Badyaev2005" ref-type="bibr">Badyaev
    2005</xref>). Obviously, the reason behind these apparent
    contradictions is that a response that appears negative at one level
    of organization or in a short time scale, at a higher level of
    organization or in a longer time scale, can enhance yield or
    fitness.</p>
    <p>It follows that when conditions are unfavourable or when there is
    a high probability that they become so, an early response such as a
    reduction in leaf-area or increase in the root:shoot biomass ratio
    accompanied by a reduction in total plant biomass are usually not an
    inevitable consequence of current stress but instead an adjustment
    to better cope with future events. A response that in the longer
    term of the whole life cycle is likely to be an improvement, in
    terms of fitness or yield, in comparison to no preemptive
    adjustment. This makes it difficult (impossible?) by simple
    observation to separate acclimation mechanisms from the direct
    consequences of stress at levels of organization below that used to
    assess fitness or yield, e.g., decreased photosynthesis and
    transpiration during drought because of stomatal closure.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="plasticity-and-anticipatory-action">
    <title>Plasticity and anticipatory action</title>
    <p>Acclimation is an induced change in the expressed genotype that
    enhances performance under one or more environmental conditions.
    Acclimation in plants is implemented as a complex syndrome of
    multiple responses at cell, tissue and organ level, frequently
    difficult to disentangle into components. Modularity, or
    discreteness, is a ubiquitous emergent property of organismic traits
    that results from the universal bounded responsiveness, to genomic
    or environmental inputs, of the phenotype at all levels of
    organization
    (<xref alt="West-Eberhard 2019" rid="ref-WestEberhard2019" ref-type="bibr">West-Eberhard
    2019</xref>). Modularity in plants’ morphology allows for a given
    genotype to produce phenotypes that not only vary in physiology and
    behavior but also vary drastically in architecture, size and
    allometry
    (<xref alt="Niklas 1994" rid="ref-Niklas1994" ref-type="bibr">Niklas
    1994</xref>). Plants also grow continuously almost until they die,
    even if long lived, and can shed parts and replace them later. In
    plants, acclimation depends frequently on adjustment of the size,
    allometry and morphology, which are slow to realize and costly to
    reverse. Timing of stress-sensitive growth stages, e.g., bud burst
    in the spring and frost hardening in the autumn in cold-climate
    perennials
    (<xref alt="Hänninen 2016" rid="ref-Hanninen2016" ref-type="bibr">Hänninen
    2016</xref>), as well as timing of the use of resources, e.g., water
    in Mediterranean climates
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>)
    also contribute to tolerance or avoidance of potential
    stress-causing events and conditions</p>
    <p>Together with a sessile mode of life, these traits make plants
    very different to animals in how they cope with variable growing
    conditions or living contexts
    (<xref alt="Huey 2002" rid="ref-Huey2002" ref-type="bibr">Huey
    2002</xref>). Acclimation in animals involves mainly regulation of
    metabolism, development and behaviour
    (<xref alt="West-Eberhard 2003" rid="ref-WestEberhard2003" ref-type="bibr">West-Eberhard
    2003</xref>). Acclimation plays a crucial role in plants’ tolerance
    of potential stress. The concept of “hardening” is older than that
    of stress, and familiar to most people who grow plants
    (<xref alt="xxxx?" rid="ref-xxxx" ref-type="bibr"><bold>xxxx?</bold></xref>).
    The term “priming” is usually used for artificially induced
    favourable acclimation responses in agricultural practice. Hardening
    and priming are types of acclimation and expressions of plasticity.
    Quantitatively, phenotypic plasticity describes the amount that the
    expression of an individual genotype can be modified by its
    environment
    (<xref alt="A. J. Trewavas and Jennings 1986" rid="ref-Trewavas1986" ref-type="bibr">A.
    J. Trewavas and Jennings 1986</xref>). These authors consider
    stability and plasticity of the phenotype to be opposites.
    Plasticity in individual phenotype tends to stabilize fitness and
    yield in the face of environmental variation. Acclimation is
    achieved through a syndrome of delicately orchestrated and
    coordinated concurrent responses of physiology, morphology and
    development, e.g., acclimation towards drought tolerance frequently
    depends on multiple cooperating mechanisms that help balance water
    supply and water use as well as mechanisms that help avoid metabolic
    and physical disruption by water deficits.</p>
    <p>Awareness of the role of acclimation and plasticity in stress
    tolerance is not new. Whitehead
    (<xref alt="1963" rid="ref-Whitehead1963" ref-type="bibr">1963</xref>)
    when discussing effects of exposure to wind writes that “…it became
    clear that any genotype has some power of reacting to the
    environment in such a way that the changes in development can be
    considered advantageous to survival under those conditions.”
    Whitehead
    (<xref alt="1963" rid="ref-Whitehead1963" ref-type="bibr">1963</xref>)
    also discussed the possible role of plant hormones in acclimation
    related to the water balance of plants and the adaptive value of
    phenotypic plasticity.</p>
    <p>Bidwell
    (<xref alt="1979" rid="ref-Bidwell1979" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>)
    was aware of the complexity involved in stress-tolerance: “The
    effects of these factors [drought, high temperature, low
    temperature, and freezing] are closely interrelated. Resistance to
    high temperature may also involve resistance to drought, which often
    accompany it. Resistance to freezing appears to be largely
    interconnected with resistance to dehydration of tissues. The
    development of hardiness to one factor often confers some degree of
    hardiness to other stresses. As a result, the study of stress
    resistance has been difficult and slow, and no far-reaching general
    theories are widely held. We shall consider special studies of
    resistance to specific stresses, but it must be continuously borne
    in mind that stress resistance is a complex and multifaceted
    phenomenon; all the details must fit into any general theory before
    it can be accepted.” He distinguishes direct effects and
    conditioning effects (what we call acclimation). He considers that
    stress always has direct effects but that conditioning effects may
    or not accompany these direct effects. A. J. Trewavas and Jennings
    (<xref alt="1986" rid="ref-Trewavas1986" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>)
    implicitly consider the problem of scaling by stating that “One
    unexpected feature to emerge is that processes of apparent
    morphological stability might hide beneath them a great deal of
    plasticity at lower levels of organization.”</p>
    <boxed-text>
    <p><bold>Note</bold></p>
    <p><bold>CHECK who is he!</bold> He also mentions parental
    environment effects mentioning research by H. R. Highkin (without a
    proper citation). The research described matches that in Highkin
    (<xref alt="1960" rid="ref-Highkin1960" ref-type="bibr">1960</xref>),
    which is a very interesting paper, and I think still relevant!”</p>
    </boxed-text>
    <p><italic>ADD TABLE 1 HERE</italic></p>
    <p>Information-acquisition by plants through sensory systems plays a
    key role in plant-plant interactions
    (<xref alt="Aphalo and Ballaré 1995" rid="ref-Aphalo1995" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Ballaré 1995</xref>;
    <xref alt="NovoplanskyXXXX?" rid="ref-NovoplanskyXXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>NovoplanskyXXXX?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>). Table 1 lists some of the sensory systems
    of plants. A role of maternal effects as well as of “memory” at a
    wide range of time scales, mechanistically based on epigenetic and
    other types of regulation, has been demonstrated for drought stress
    tolerance
    (<xref alt="Ariel Novoplansky 2009" rid="ref-Novoplansky2009" ref-type="bibr">Ariel
    Novoplansky 2009</xref>;
    <xref alt="Hagai Shemesh et al. 2010" rid="ref-Shemesh2010" ref-type="bibr">Hagai
    Shemesh et al. 2010</xref>;
    <xref alt="Falik, Mauda, and Novoplansky 2022" rid="ref-Falik2022" ref-type="bibr">Falik,
    Mauda, and Novoplansky 2022</xref>). The implication is that at any
    time in the life history of a plant how this plant responds to the
    environment depends not only on its genotype, but also on its
    physical state and how the “memory” of pasts events affects the
    “set-points” of the vast transduction network that regulates gene
    expression, plant metabolism, growth and development—from a control
    systems’ perspective, “decision-making”
    (<xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>).</p>
    <p>While clear evidence of airborne plant-to-plant communication
    mediated by emitted chemical signals in herbivory has been available
    for some years (e.g.,
    <xref alt="Holopainen and Gershenzon 2010" rid="ref-Holopainen2010" ref-type="bibr">Holopainen
    and Gershenzon 2010</xref>;
    <xref alt="Pierik, Ballaré, and Dicke 2014" rid="ref-Pierik2014" ref-type="bibr">Pierik,
    Ballaré, and Dicke 2014</xref>;
    <xref alt="Šimpraga et al. 2019" rid="ref-Simpraga2019" ref-type="bibr">Šimpraga
    et al. 2019</xref>), recent work has demonstrated soil-borne
    root-root communication in the case of drought and salinity
    (<xref alt="Falik, Mauda, and Novoplansky 2022" rid="ref-Falik2022" ref-type="bibr">Falik,
    Mauda, and Novoplansky 2022</xref>). These signals are not only
    communicated between immediate neighbouring plants but are also
    relayed ahead by the individuals perceiving them to individuals not
    directly sharing soil with the initial emitter
    (<xref alt="Falik et al. 2011" rid="ref-Falik2011" ref-type="bibr">Falik
    et al. 2011</xref>). Furthermore, these signals, in both cases
    trigger in the “receiver” responses that enhance future tolerance of
    the stressor experienced by the “emitter”. Although surprising in
    their sophistication, these mechanisms make sense from an
    evolutionary perspective as they can be expected to enhance fitness
    (<xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>), at least in some cases, of all participants
    in the communication. According to
    (<xref alt="Godfrey-Smith 2014" rid="ref-GodfreySmith2014" ref-type="bibr">Godfrey-Smith
    2014</xref>) “The evolution of cooperation has become integral to
    our understanding of the workings and origins of living things.”</p>
    <p>Aphalo and Sadras
    (<xref alt="2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>)
    proposed a model integrating resources and information as drivers of
    the plant phenotype. They highlight processes that can lead to
    pre-emptive acclimation or preparedness, while the environmental?
    variables acting as cues need only be good “predictors” of future
    conditions, thus not necessarily factors that cause strain in the
    plant. For example, exposure to ultraviolet-B radiation can be a
    cause of strain but is also a source of information for the
    regulation of gene expression, metabolism and growth in the absence
    of detectable stress
    (<xref alt="Jansen and Potters 2017" rid="ref-Jansen2017" ref-type="bibr">Jansen
    and Potters 2017</xref>).</p>
    <p>Following exposure to a potential stressor a plant “may” or “may
    not” be under stress because strain depends on its current state or
    phenotype. In other words, strain is the result of an interaction
    between an organism’s phenotype and its environment, and for any
    variable to be called a “stressor” it must disrupt an organism’s
    function at a specific point in time. A fully acclimated plant will
    not be strained by a potential stressor, even if preemptive
    acclimation has required a controlled reduction in its growth rate.
    Maximizing growth is not necessarily adaptive in nature or
    profitable/sustainable in agriculture, and this is a major issue in
    growth-based definitions of stress (Box 2). To fully avoid strain,
    acclimation must precede exposure to potential stressor. On the
    other hand, when acclimation prevents strain at the cost of a
    “controlled” decrease in growth or yield, the potential stressor
    behaves as a limitation. From this follows, that an informational
    cue or signal can also limit growth and/or yield.</p>
    <p>The success of anticipatory action towards future recurring
    conditions that are subject to “random” variation in occurrence and
    intensity cannot be evaluated deterministically. Replication in time
    and space is needed so that response is assessed over a
    multidimensional “space” that encompasses the range of environmental
    variation of interest. This is why extensive field trial networks
    are used at late steps of crop breeding. As communication among
    individuals and maternal effects play a role, they also need to be
    taken into account, e.g., using field plots instead of individual
    plants in pots.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="levels-of-organization-and-interactions">
    <title>Levels of organization and interactions</title>
    <p>Levels of organization and hierarchical organization of systems
    are central to contemporary biological thinking
    (<xref alt="Wimsatt 1976" rid="ref-Wimsatt1976" ref-type="bibr">Wimsatt
    1976</xref>,
    <xref alt="1994" rid="ref-Wimsatt1994" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>;
    <xref alt="Capra and Luisi 2014" rid="ref-Capra2014" ref-type="bibr">Capra
    and Luisi 2014</xref>;
    <xref alt="Sadras2016?" rid="ref-Sadras2016" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Sadras2016?</bold></xref>;
    Sadras and Richards 2016,
    <xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>;
    <xref alt="Kauffman and Roli 2023" rid="ref-Kauffman2023" ref-type="bibr">Kauffman
    and Roli 2023</xref>; Kauffman and Roli 2023,
    <xref alt="Thorogood et al. 2023" rid="ref-Thorogood2023" ref-type="bibr">Thorogood
    et al. 2023</xref>). Compositional levels of organization are
    defined as hierarchical divisions of biological entities ‘organized
    by part-whole relations in which wholes at one level function as
    parts at the next (and all higher) levels’
    (<xref alt="Wimsatt 1994" rid="ref-Wimsatt1994" ref-type="bibr">Wimsatt
    1994</xref>). In the words of Kauffman and Roli
    (<xref alt="2023" rid="ref-Kauffman2023" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>)
    “…living things are Kantian wholes where the parts exist in the
    universe for and by means of the whole.” Because individuals, as
    Kantian wholes, propagate their offspring, their sustaining parts -
    lungs and kidneys in mammals – “are also propagated and evolve to
    function better”
    (<xref alt="Kauffman and Roli 2023" rid="ref-Kauffman2023" ref-type="bibr">Kauffman
    and Roli 2023</xref>). Levels ‘are constituted by families of
    entities usually of comparable size and dynamical properties, which
    characteristically interact primarily with one another’
    (<xref alt="Wimsatt 1994" rid="ref-Wimsatt1994" ref-type="bibr">Wimsatt
    1994</xref>). Notwithstanding cross-level interactions,
    (<xref alt="Wimsatt 1994" rid="ref-Wimsatt1994" ref-type="bibr">Wimsatt
    1994</xref>) view highlights that molecules interact mostly with
    molecules
    (<xref alt="Rietman2011?" rid="ref-Rietman2011" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Rietman2011?</bold></xref>)
    and plants with plants
    (<xref alt="Harper1977?" rid="ref-Harper1977" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Harper1977?</bold></xref>);
    this partially accounts for the compartmentalized theories
    associated with each level. Indeed, processes can be separated into
    discrete classes by their time constants
    (<xref alt="Levins1970?" rid="ref-Levins1970" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Levins1970?</bold></xref>).
    A physiological perspective challenging the cause-and-effect arrow
    from genotype to phenotype led to the conclusion that there is no
    privileged level of organisation and highlighted the importance of
    downward causation in the construction of the phenotype whereby
    higher-level properties “necessarily also causes of lower level
    behaviour, involving actions and interactions both ways”
    (<xref alt="Noble 2012" rid="ref-Noble2012" ref-type="bibr">Noble
    2012</xref>). Below we apply these ideas in an attempt to illuminate
    the concepts of stress, stressor and strain.</p>
    <p>As discussed in previous sections, potential and actual stressors
    in nature are rarely individual environmental factors but instead
    combinations of factors acting jointly or sequentially. Information
    acquired by plants through the perception of cues and signals in the
    environment is combined during transduction
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    Acquired information and experienced stress drastically affect
    future responses to both informational cues and signals, and to
    potential stressors thanks to changes in readiness to respond and
    physiological, morphological and developmental acclimation. The more
    we learn about the molecular and physiological mechanisms of stress,
    the more intractable the problem appears. One difficulty, we think,
    is attempting to force this knowledge into two boxes by assuming
    that stress is distinct from normal, i.e., that there is a
    dichotomy. The two extreme conditions are exceptional. Realization
    of potential fitness or crop yield is almost never achieved in
    practice and death after stablishment leaving no offspring is not
    very common in plants, while predation on seeds and death of
    seedlings can be frequent. In the case of populations, complete
    extinction is infrequent. Most individual plants and populations
    function somewhere between these limits. So, if we take optimal
    conditions as a reference, we can conclude that nearly all plants
    are strained. In contrast, if we define strain as a terminal
    disruption leading to premature plant death or no offspring, we can
    conclude that strain is a very exceptional condition. Both of these
    views, fail to recognize that intermediate degrees of strain and the
    gradual transition between the extreme situations and its dynamics
    in time and space are the most interesting.</p>
    <p>Hierarchical, thus asymmetrical, organization of living systems
    precludes upscaling and downscaling stressed states
    (<xref alt="Noble 2012" rid="ref-Noble2012" ref-type="bibr">Noble
    2012</xref>,
    <xref alt="2017" rid="ref-Noble2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>;
    <xref alt="Passioura 2010" rid="ref-Passioura2010" ref-type="bibr">Passioura
    2010</xref>,
    <xref alt="2020" rid="ref-Passioura2020" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).
    This is a feature of biological systems that affects all definitions
    of stress, stressor and strain. Thus, we need caution in using signs
    of metabolic and physiological strain (sensu Levitt) to characterize
    whole-organism, in our case, whole-plant strain. Similarly, signs of
    strain in individual plants cannot be directly used to assess strain
    at population, community or ecosystem levels. Stress definitions at
    levels of organization below the individual plant are frequently
    used in physiology and molecular biology, but these definitions have
    little in common with those at higher levels of organization. This
    low-level approach consists of defining one or more specific
    disruptions (i.e., stress or strain) in an organism’s metabolic or
    cellular function as a measure of stress. In many cases, criteria
    are based on an observable state, and thus easily quantifiable, such
    as for example gene expression, quantum yield of photosystem II,
    membrane leakage, and the total anti-oxidant capacity. In the
    context of reductionist biotechnology, for example, Vinocur and
    Altman {, 2005 #5260} define primary stresses with a focus on
    environmental factor, such as cold stress or salinity stress, and
    define a secondary stress with a focus on processes, such as osmotic
    stress or oxidative stress. Their conceptual framework scales up to
    cellular homeostasis, but not beyond. The connection between stress
    on individual cells and whole-plant stress is often tenuous, to the
    point that what is called stress at these lower levels often drives
    acclimation that makes possible full avoidance of stress at the
    whole plant and population levels. For example, enhanced drought
    tolerance in virus-infected plants has been attributed to increased
    levels of antioxidants and osmoprotectants partially mediated by
    increased protein hydroxylation, and interference with crosstalk
    between abscisic acid (ABA) and salicylic acid (SA)
    (<xref alt="Mishraet2022?" rid="ref-Mishraet2022" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Mishraet2022?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="Prasad2022?" rid="ref-Prasad2022" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Prasad2022?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="Szczepaniec2019?" rid="ref-Szczepaniec2019" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Szczepaniec2019?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="vanMunster2020?" rid="ref-vanMunster2020" ref-type="bibr"><bold>vanMunster2020?</bold></xref>).
    The combination of infection with tomato yellow leaf curl Sardinia
    virus (TYLCSV) and water deficit in glasshouse-grown tomato
    Moneymaker was antagonistic for stem water potential, which was
    -0.36 MPa in well-watered, mock-inoculated controls and dropped to
    -1.51 MPa under water stress with no virus, but only to -0.95 MPa in
    water-stressed plants inoculated with TYLCSV
    (<xref alt="Sadras2023?" rid="ref-Sadras2023" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Sadras2023?</bold></xref>)
    <italic>(Sadras et al 2023)</italic>. Scaling down to gene
    expression, the effect of virus infection and drought stress was
    additive for the expression of three genes: SINCED1, associated with
    ABA biosynthesis, ABA-responsive dehydrin SITAS14 and auxin response
    factor SIARF8. An antagonistic interaction between virus and water
    regime was detected for the expression of SlCYP707A2 associated with
    ABA degradation. Scaling up to plant growth, an antagonistic effect
    between virus and drought stress was apparent for plant height, but
    not for plant fresh weight and root length that showed additive
    effects. A quantitative review with this kind of analysis reached
    the conclusion that “shifts in gene expression and common metabolic
    pathways between plant defence and response to drought stress are
    insightful but fall short in relevance in the absence of scaling”
    (<xref alt="Sadras2023?" rid="ref-Sadras2023" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Sadras2023?</bold></xref>).</p>
    <p>Density-dependence and oversimplified experimental settings
    further compromise scaling. Density-dependent traits such as canopy
    photosynthesis and crop yield do not scale from plant to stand
    (<xref alt="Sinclair2004?" rid="ref-Sinclair2004" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Sinclair2004?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="Pettigrew1989?" rid="ref-Pettigrew1989" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Pettigrew1989?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="Pedro2012?" rid="ref-Pedro2012" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Pedro2012?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="Lake2016?" rid="ref-Lake2016" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Lake2016?</bold></xref>).
    In his compilation of data on the fertility of hybrids,
    (<xref alt="Darwin 1859, 247" rid="ref-Darwin1859" ref-type="bibr">Darwin
    1859, 247</xref>) dismisses some observations on the grounds of
    experimental artefacts: “Nearly all the plants experimentised on by
    Gartner were potted, and apparently were kept in a chamber in his
    house. That these processes are often injurious to the fertility of
    a plant cannot be doubted”. Small pots and the imposition of sudden,
    severe water deficit do not allow, for example, for plant
    acclimation and realistic root patterns, particularly in long-lived
    perennials with extensive root systems. The metabolism of
    sunlight-grown plants does not match that of plants grown under
    artificial light regimes
    (<xref alt="Annunziata2017?" rid="ref-Annunziata2017" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Annunziata2017?</bold></xref>);
    field validation is essential. Where the objective is crop
    improvement, the pipleline from lab to field can be reversed to an
    effective field to lab approach
    (<xref alt="Thistlethwaite2020?" rid="ref-Thistlethwaite2020" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Thistlethwaite2020?</bold></xref>).</p>
    <p>Time and its progression are important, as fitness is achieved
    through an individual’s life time, and in annual plants achieved
    only towards the end of the life cycle. As growth and development
    progresses, the remaining available routes for plasticity decrease,
    and this forces a change in strategy as a plant develops
    (<xref alt="H. Shemesh and Novoplansky 2013" rid="ref-Shemesh2013" ref-type="bibr">H.
    Shemesh and Novoplansky 2013</xref>) <italic>(Shemesh and
    Novoplansky, 2013)</italic>. This decreasing ability for acclimation
    concurrent with development and growth, can make successful
    anticipation and early “decision making” highly beneficial to
    fitness. Heritability, median across cereal crops, increases from
    0.31 for tiller number established early in the season, to 0.58 for
    inflorescence number, to 0.59 for grains per inflorescence, and to
    0.79 for grain size established later in the growing season
    (<xref alt="Sadras2012?" rid="ref-Sadras2012" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Sadras2012?</bold></xref>).
    This supports a hierarchy of phenotypic plasticities (sensu
    <xref alt="Bradshaw 1965" rid="ref-Bradshaw1965" ref-type="bibr">Bradshaw
    1965</xref>): tiller number &gt; inflorescence number ≈ grains per
    inflorescence &gt; seed size. This strong hierarchy has been
    attributed to the differential fitness contribution from each trait,
    which is reinforced by the increase in interference between
    neighbouring plants and associated reduction in availability of
    resources per plant as the crop cycle progresses
    (<xref alt="Sadras2012?" rid="ref-Sadras2012" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Sadras2012?</bold></xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="stress-as-maladaptation">
    <title>Stress as maladaptation</title>
    <p>The viewpoint that “stressful environments hardly exist”
    (<xref alt="Körner 2003" rid="ref-Koerner2003" ref-type="bibr">Körner
    2003</xref>) implies considering stress as caused by maladaptation
    at the population level. Such a definition makes stress directly
    dependent on local and/or global directional change of the biotic
    and/or abiotic environment. However, when considering individual
    plants, and normal genetic and environmental variation, at any point
    in time some genotypes in a population will have transiently higher
    or lower fitness than other genotypes. Individual plants may be less
    than optimally adapted to the current environment and thus under
    strain. Thus, maladaptation can be a useful criterion of stress both
    at individual and population levels of organization, especially for
    studies related to environmental change and ecology and evolution.
    For example, the timing of exposure to a potential stressor (e.g.,
    drought) or benefactor (e.g., presence of pollinators) relative to
    phenological phases of development of wild and crop plants is
    crucial for fitness and yield, respectively
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    Already Darwin
    (<xref alt="1859" rid="ref-Darwin1859" ref-type="bibr">1859</xref>)
    observed “…very trifling changes, such as a little more or less
    water at some particular period of growth, will determine whether or
    not the plant sets a grain”.</p>
    <p>When considering global change, it is unlikely that a response
    has not been subjected to natural selection under a somehow similar
    although less extreme condition. Consequently, acclimation being
    ubiquitous will coexist with accidental responses to a challenge of
    novel intensity. Pre-adaptations or affordances (see
    <xref alt="Kauffman and Roli 2023" rid="ref-Kauffman2023" ref-type="bibr">Kauffman
    and Roli 2023</xref>) can also “happen” to help towards tolerance of
    environmental conditions never experienced by an individual’s
    ancestors making the distinction between selected-for responses and
    those that are purely accidental even more difficult. The situation
    is to an extent different when considering synthetic chemicals and
    pollution or foreign invasive species, as these can be qualitatively
    novel challenges.</p>
    <p>A similar approach but using as measure of performance a
    commercially relevant quantity (such as yield) instead of fitness is
    applicable to crop breeding. This is so because crop breeding aims
    in most cases at enhanced production or stability of production in a
    well-defined environment, e.g., a specific geographic region or
    farming system. In agriculture, the role of timing is reflected in
    the concept of a critical-developmental-stage, which is central to
    crop physiology: e.g., probabilistic patterns of drought type have
    been developed for major crops that account for timing (relative to
    plant development), intensity and duration of stress inducing
    condition, and pairing of genotype and environment to predict
    stress. An ability to predict the effects on yield of stress during
    critical developmental periods is central to crop management
    <italic>(references to follow if we include these
    concepts)</italic>.</p>
    <p>Stress definitions at levels of organization below the individual
    plant are frequently used in physiological and molecular biology
    research, but these definitions have little in common with those at
    higher levels of organization. The criteria frequently used are no
    longer directly relevant to natural selection or crop production
    because they assess only small portions of the complex biological
    systems that determine the outcomes that are relevant to evolution
    or to agriculture.</p>
    <p>This low level approach consists of defining one or more specific
    disruptions (i.e., stress or strain) in an organism’s metabolic or
    cellular function as a measure to asses stress. In many cases,
    criteria are based on an observable state, and thus easily
    quantifiable, such as for example the quantum yield of photosystem
    II, membrane leakage, and the total anti-oxidant capacity. The
    connection between stress on individual cells and whole-plant stress
    is tenuous, to the point that what is called stress at these lower
    levels in many cases drives acclimation that makes possible full
    avoidance of stress at the whole plant and population levels.
    Physiological stress can have both positive and negative effects on
    the plant as a whole. Thus these criteria, which inform about
    specific mechanisms, are no substitute for the assessment of stress
    and strain at higher levels of organization.</p>
    <p>The action of a stressor is easy to assess when we are strained
    by it. How can we decide if a plant is strained or not, when
    acclimation involves so many alterations to the phenotype? This
    question is particularly relevant where stress or acclimation
    responses are superficially similar, such as is the case for
    salinity tolerance where smaller leaves may reflect stress-mediated
    disruption of cell elongation, or an active acclimation response
    that can facilitate a decrease in transpiration
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    In many cases, stress has been defined based on a human-benefit
    perspective, e.g., a decrease in yield, or reduced growth. However,
    some stress adapted plants such as metallophytes also grow slowly,
    demonstrating that decreased biomass production cannot a priory be
    perceived as stress; indeed, slow growth can be adaptive in some
    agronomic and natural settings (Box 2). If we accept this type of
    definitions one needs to accept that in nature, being the growth of
    any plant in one way or another limited by factors external to it,
    all plants are under stress. Such definitions are irrelevant to the
    study of biological mechanisms, even if relevant to management of
    production systems.</p>
    <p>Stressed humans fail to make good decisions or in extreme cases
    cannot make any decision
    (<xref alt="Molins, Serrano, and Alacreu-Crespo 2021" rid="ref-Molins2021" ref-type="bibr">Molins,
    Serrano, and Alacreu-Crespo 2021</xref>;
    <xref alt="Wu2020?" rid="ref-Wu2020" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Wu2020?</bold></xref>)
    <italic>(Molins, Serrano, and Alacreu-Crespo 2021;
    Wu-et-al2020?)</italic>. Surprisingly, this could work as a good
    definition of stress also for plants! A plant that grows more leaves
    when it is lacking water is stressed, but a plant that grows more
    roots is not, because it displays an adaptive response to its
    environment. Even a plant shedding leaves when lacking water is not
    necessarily stressed, as this is a good way of saving water from a
    plant’s perspective, at least in an “emergency situation”.</p>
    <p>How the “goodness of a decision” can be formally assessed? For
    wild plants the criterion for good decision making is long-term
    fitness, and for crops its contribution to long-term yield, its
    stability and/or produce quality, i.e., the selection criteria, of
    natural selection and crop breeding, respectively.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="measurement-of-acclimation-and-strain">
  <title>Measurement of acclimation and strain</title>
  <p>The practical measurement or detection of acclimation and stress
  have been based on the measurement of a large number of different
  state variables in plants, their parts or their assemblages. This is
  natural given the complexity of biological systems and the many
  different potential stressors that can be present in the environment.
  A very frequently used criterion at whole-plant and above levels of
  organization has been aboveground biomass production rate, however,
  this criterion has no thoeretical basis and is only weakly corelated
  to fitness of individuals, crop yield or ecosystem stability (Box
  1).</p>
  <boxed-text>
  <p><bold>Slow growth could be adaptive in some natural and
  agricultural scenarios</bold></p>
  <p>Here we sample relationships between growth and defense, aspects of
  reproductive allocation, and seasonal patterns of water use to reach
  the conclusion that maximizing growth is not necessarily adaptive in
  nature or profitable in agriculture. The implication is that
  growth-based definitions of stress are at best incomplete and at worst
  flawed.</p>
  <p>An allometric analysis of <italic>Daphnia mitsukuri</italic>
  exposed to predatory fish kairomone showed enhanced resource
  allocation to tail spine, a defense trait, and decreased body growth
  rate that did not compromise reproduction in comparison to untreated
  controls
  (<xref alt="Gu et al. 2021" rid="ref-Gu2021" ref-type="bibr">Gu et al.
  2021</xref>). In a set of four clones, increased resource allocation
  to tail spine was associated with reduced growth. This negative
  correlation was not interpreted in terms of a trade-off, but as a
  double adaptation: a larger defensive tail spine, and smaller
  individuals that are less conspicuous and provide less energy to the
  predatory fish
  (<xref alt="Gu et al. 2021" rid="ref-Gu2021" ref-type="bibr">Gu et al.
  2021</xref>). Marine planktonic crustaceans reduce feeding activity in
  the presence of fish kairomones and the resulting reduction in gut
  fullness has been proposed to be adaptive in reducing visibility to
  predators
  (<xref alt="Lass and Spaak 2003" rid="ref-Lass2003" ref-type="bibr">Lass
  and Spaak 2003</xref>). However, size preference varies with predation
  strategy, e.g., planktivorous fish hunt visually and prefer larger
  Daphnia prey, whereas larvae of the phantom midge
  <italic>Chaoborus</italic> are tactile hunters and prefer smaller
  <italic>Daphnia</italic>
  (<xref alt="Lass and Spaak 2003" rid="ref-Lass2003" ref-type="bibr">Lass
  and Spaak 2003</xref>). In the facultative symbiotic association
  between isopods and red wood ants (<italic>Formica rufa</italic>
  group), a smaller body size in ant associates decreases their
  detection by the host
  (<xref alt="Zarka et al. 2022" rid="ref-Zarka2022" ref-type="bibr">Zarka
  et al. 2022</xref>).</p>
  <p>Cacti combine slow growth as an adaptation to extremely dry
  conditions and a wide array of secondary metabolites involved in
  defence against biotic and abiotic stresses including alkaloids,
  phenolic compounds, and terpenes
  (<xref alt="Santos-Díaz and Camarena-Rangel 2019" rid="ref-SantosDiaz2019" ref-type="bibr">Santos-Díaz
  and Camarena-Rangel 2019</xref>). In crowded stands, a common
  expectation is for the higher fitness of larger plants able to capture
  resources and deny them to neighbours. However, the frequency
  distribution of plant species body size is L-shaped within every
  phylogenetic lineage, and for resident species at every spatial scale
  – from regional floras down to local neighbourhoods
  (<xref alt="Aarssen 2015" rid="ref-Aarssen2015" ref-type="bibr">Aarssen
  2015</xref>). To account for the mismatch between the expected
  dominance of large species and the observations, Aarssen
  (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-Aarssen2015" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>)
  has shifted the focus from capture of resources and growth to
  reproduction, whereby smaller species are more likely to reach a size
  threshold for reproduction in a conceptual model accounting to
  availability of resources and time available to reach the reproductive
  threshold as affected by disturbances, including herbivory.</p>
  <p>In the context of plant domestication in the ancient Near East,
  slow growth is listed as an adaptation to grazing alongside thorns,
  toxicity, and underground storage organs
  (<xref alt="Abbo, Gopher, and Bar-Gal 2022" rid="ref-Abbo2022" ref-type="bibr">Abbo,
  Gopher, and Bar-Gal 2022</xref>). For annual crops relying on stored
  soil water, slow vegetative growth could be adaptive as a larger
  fraction of soil water is available during the critical period of seed
  set and filling; traits associated with slow vegetative growth in
  wheat include low hydraulic conductance associated with narrow xylem
  vessels in the seminal roots
  (<xref alt="Richards and Passioura 1981" rid="ref-Richards1981a" ref-type="bibr">Richards
  and Passioura 1981</xref>,
  <xref alt="1989" rid="ref-Richards1989" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>);
  higher sensitivity of plant transpiration to vapour pressure deficit
  (<xref alt="Schoppach et al. 2017" rid="ref-Schoppach2017" ref-type="bibr">Schoppach
  et al. 2017</xref>), and reduced root biomass, tillering and leaf area
  with maintenance of stomatal conductance and photosynthesis per unit
  leaf area in response to dry soil
  (<xref alt="Khan et al. 2022" rid="ref-Khan2022" ref-type="bibr">Khan
  et al. 2022</xref>). The implications of these traits for plant
  defence, if any, are unknown. In field-grown winter wheat, mechanical
  trimming of roots at the onset of spring growth also displaced the
  pattern of water use in favour of reproductive stages and increased
  yield in comparison to controls with intact root systems
  (<xref alt="Hu et al. 2019" rid="ref-Hu2019" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al.
  2019</xref>); root pruning increased the amount and concentration of
  labile carbohydrates in shoots, which play a putative role as osmotic
  defence against aphids
  (<xref alt="Sadras2021?" rid="ref-Sadras2021" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Sadras2021?</bold></xref>;
  <xref alt="Ramirez2023?" rid="ref-Ramirez2023" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Ramirez2023?</bold></xref>)
  (Sadras, 2021){Ramírez, 2023 #21197}. Imposition of mild water stress
  through the suspension or reduction of irrigation at the end of the
  growing season, known as ’drying-off”, is a common practice to
  increase concentration of sugar in shoot and sugar yield in commercial
  sugarcane fields
  (<xref alt="Singels2021?" rid="ref-Singels2021" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Singels2021?</bold></xref>)
  {Singels, 2021 #21856}.</p>
  </boxed-text>
  <p>Selye
  (<xref alt="1975" rid="ref-Selye1975" ref-type="bibr">1975</xref>)
  tells “…the stress syndrome is — by definition — nonspecific in its
  causation. However, depending upon conditioning factors, which can
  selectively influence the reactivity of certain organs, the same
  stressor can elicit different manifestations in different
  individuals.” This view of the <italic>stress syndrome</italic> is an
  abstract one. It implies that the <italic>stress syndrome</italic>
  abstraction encompasses stress caused by different stressors and
  mediated by shared underlying mechanisms. We now know that the
  mechanisms involved vary, specially in plants, even if in some cases
  some underlying responses are shared. Thus, it is natural that many
  ways of detecting and measuring stress are in use. As these different
  approaches can be more or less specific to different underlying
  mechanisms of stress, the diagnosis or measurements based on them are
  likely to yield inconsistent results. In
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="fig-indicators-of-stress">Figure 1</xref> we
  list several of the measures used to detect and quantify stress at
  different levels of organization.</p>
  <fig id="fig-indicators-of-stress">
    <caption><p>Figure 1: Diagram showing commonly used indicators of
    strain at different levels of organization. The rightmost column of
    boxes shows variables or parameters used to diagnose
    <italic>strain</italic> or the existance of stress in plants and
    their assemblages.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files\figure-jats\mermaid-figure-5.png" />
  </fig>
  <p>While in many cases the detection or measurement of strain is
  possible at a single point in time, this is rarely possible for
  acclimation. The detection of stress-aleviating or stress-preventing
  acclimation to be reliable requires the observation of a time-course
  of responses, starting before strain develops. As acclimation implies
  a cost, distinguishing acclimation from strain and limitation is
  difficult. At an early stage the criteria that are used for
  acclimation differ to some extent from those used for stress
  (<xref alt="Figure 2" rid="fig-indicators-of-acclimation">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
  <fig id="fig-indicators-of-acclimation">
    <caption><p>Figure 2: Diagram showing commonly used immediate
    indicators of acclimation at different levels of organization. The
    rightmost column of boxes shows variables or parameters used to
    diagnose <italic>acclimation</italic> or _the existance of
    favourable plastic responses in plants and their
    assemblages.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files\figure-jats\mermaid-figure-8.png" />
  </fig>
  <p>To assess if acclimation has been effective in protecting from
  stress, we assess strain at some point(s) in time after we assume
  acclimation has become effective by assessing the response to a
  stressor
  (<xref alt="Figure 3" rid="fig-value-of-acclimation">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
  <fig id="fig-value-of-acclimation">
    <caption><p>Figure 3: Diagram showing the temporal sequence used to
    assess acclimation efectiveness in the context of stress as parallel
    time lines for <italic>treatment</italic> and
    <italic>control</italic>.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/fig-value-of-acclimation-1.png" />
  </fig>
  <boxed-text>
  <p><bold>Reaction norms and the quantification of strain</bold></p>
  <p>In the context of environmental variation, reaction norms relating
  the phenotype and environmental factors
  (<xref alt="Woltereck 1909" rid="ref-Woltereck1909" ref-type="bibr">Woltereck
  1909</xref>) facilitate operational definitions of strain that are
  useful in modelling and insightful physiologically. A common modelling
  approach is to define the potential for a trait, e.g., photosynthetic
  rate, and scale the potential to account for factors such as water
  deficit, nutrient deficiency, or atmospheric ozone
  (<xref alt="Guarin et al. 2019" rid="ref-Guarin2019" ref-type="bibr">Guarin
  et al. 2019</xref>) (Guarin et al., 2019). Figure 2 (left) shows the
  reaction norm of maize leaf expansion rate in response to
  meristem-to-air vapour pressure deficit. The reaction norm defines
  three traits: the leaf expansion rate at VPD = 0 is the intrinsic or
  potential rate in the absence of stress, the slope is the phenotypic
  plasticity, and the x-intercept is the vapour pressure deficit that
  completely inhibits expansion. All three traits are genotype-dependent
  and map to particular genomic regions (Fig. 2, right). Of particular
  interest in this article, nine QTL were identified for the intrinsic
  rate of expansion, the non-stressful condition, and six for its
  phenotypic plasticity, with only two of them overlapping
  (<xref alt="Reymond et al. 2003" rid="ref-Reymond2003" ref-type="bibr">Reymond
  et al. 2003</xref>). This supports Bradshaw’s
  (<xref alt="Bradshaw 1965" rid="ref-Bradshaw1965" ref-type="bibr">Bradshaw
  1965</xref>) early prediction of the partial independence of the
  genetic modulation of the trait itself and its plasticity.</p>
  <p><italic>Figures 1 and 2</italic> to be added around here.</p>
  </boxed-text>
  <sec id="the-difference-between-stress-and-limitation">
    <title>The difference between stress and limitation</title>
    <p>The use of the concept of “limitation” differs from the use of
    “stress/strain” discussed above in that it most frequently refers to
    “variables” that are quantified on a continuous scale. In many, but
    not all cases, they are also resources that plants use up when
    growing.</p>
    <p>While stress and strain have their roots in Physics, “limitation”
    has its roots in economy. Its meaning is in most cases unambiguous
    from the context of its use: there is always a sought-after outcome
    and a constraint on it. This contrasts with the multiple meanings of
    “stress”. When stress is used as a synonym of stressor, e.g., the
    statement “the crop is under drought stress”, it is close in meaning
    to “…limited by insufficient water supply”.
    In this approach, stress is typically assessed based on the
    comparison of performance under two conditions, one that does not
    impose a persistent limitation on a target response and one that
    limits it. Usually the limiting environmental state is an
    exceptional one, and the reference a “normal” one.</p>
    <p>In agriculture, to assess for example the impact of drought at
    the field-scale, frequently a comparison of crop yield is done
    between normal years and a drought years and across sites. This is
    generally only meaningful when done regionally, collecting data over
    several years, rather than by comparing cropping systems with
    markedly different average yield levels. However, for a researcher
    interested in a specific physiological mechanism such an approach
    can be inadequate as the multiple conditions can differ in too many
    poorly defined aspects, making necessary very long-term studies to
    untangle the role of individual limitations. Conversely, typical
    experiments in controlled conditions that drastically differ from
    those in the field, or that assess performance using physiological
    parameters, such as membrane leakage or DNA damage fail to inform
    about any potential cost on crop yield and/or plant fitness
    (<xref alt="Sadras 2020" rid="ref-Sadras2020" ref-type="bibr">Sadras
    2020</xref>) (Sadras et al. 2020). However, these experiments yield
    publishable results in a much shorter time than long-term field
    trials.</p>
    <p>As an optimal, non-limiting condition is unlikely in the natural
    or managed environment, using such a reference is of little
    practical use to agriculture or ecology
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="KoernerXXXX?" rid="ref-KoernerXXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>KoernerXXXX?</bold></xref>).
    Furthermore, the definition of optimal conditions is very difficult:
    for example silver birch seedlings under continuous light cultivated
    using aeroponics with nutrient supply proportional to the growth
    rate can attain a relative growth rate, measured as dry mass, of 27%
    per day, but such conditions are unlike those in nature
    (<xref alt="Ågren and Weih 2012" rid="ref-Agren2012" ref-type="bibr">Ågren
    and Weih 2012</xref>) <italic>(Ågren and Weih, 2012)</italic>. In
    practice, the control or reference growing environment is less
    limiting than the growth-limiting one, but it rarely allows the
    maximum potential growth rate.</p>
    <p>In agriculture the concept of limitation has a clear meaning. For
    example, fertilisation and irrigation alleviate limitations, often
    increase crop yield, and have driven much of the sustained increase
    in global food production over decades
    (<xref alt="Sinclair and Rufty 2012" rid="ref-Sinclair2012" ref-type="bibr">Sinclair
    and Rufty 2012</xref>) <italic>(Sinclair and Rufty 2012)</italic>.
    The concept of limitation leads to useful operational definitions in
    agriculture (Fig. 1). Based on economic analogies, ecological theory
    predicts that plant growth <italic>efficiency?</italic> is maximised
    when all resources are equally limiting
    (<xref alt="Bloom, Chapin, and Mooney 1985" rid="ref-Bloom1985" ref-type="bibr">Bloom,
    Chapin, and Mooney 1985</xref>) <italic>(Bloom et al.,
    1985)</italic>. This leads to the concept of co-limitation, which is
    grounded on robust theory and quantitative approaches to frame the
    empirical evidence
    (<xref alt="Bracken2015?" rid="ref-Bracken2015" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Bracken2015?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="Cossani and Sadras 2018" rid="ref-Cossani2018" ref-type="bibr">Cossani
    and Sadras 2018</xref>;
    <xref alt="Elser et al. 2007" rid="ref-Elser2007" ref-type="bibr">Elser
    et al. 2007</xref>;
    <xref alt="Harpole et al. 2011" rid="ref-Harpole2011" ref-type="bibr">Harpole
    et al. 2011</xref>;
    <xref alt="Kho 2000" rid="ref-Kho2000" ref-type="bibr">Kho
    2000</xref>;
    <xref alt="Sperfeld2016?" rid="ref-Sperfeld2016" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Sperfeld2016?</bold></xref>).
    For example, we have gained insights on the primary production of
    diverse ecosystems that from the perspective of nitrogen-phosphorus
    co-limitation and on the seed yield of rainfed crops from the angle
    of nitrogen-water co-limitation
    (<xref alt="Elser et al. 2007" rid="ref-Elser2007" ref-type="bibr">Elser
    et al. 2007</xref>;
    <xref alt="Harpole et al. 2011" rid="ref-Harpole2011" ref-type="bibr">Harpole
    et al. 2011</xref>;
    <xref alt="Sperfeld2016?" rid="ref-Sperfeld2016" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Sperfeld2016?</bold></xref>;
    <xref alt="Cossani and Sadras 2018" rid="ref-Cossani2018" ref-type="bibr">Cossani
    and Sadras 2018</xref>). Scaling to three or more co-limiting
    factors remains a challenge
    (<xref alt="Cossani and Sadras 2018" rid="ref-Cossani2018" ref-type="bibr">Cossani
    and Sadras 2018</xref>).</p>
    <p>The usefulness of the concept of limitation breaks down when
    considering the ecology and evolution of plant species: “watering
    the desert, fertilizing the tundra, warming the alpine zone, … are
    commonly fatal for the plants living there, creating a completely
    new assemblage of species, with the former ‘limited’ ones being
    eliminated”
    (<xref alt="Körner 2003" rid="ref-Koerner2003" ref-type="bibr">Körner
    2003</xref>). The concept of limitations or constraints can be
    applied when considering ecosystem pools and fluxes (e.g.,
    <xref alt="Chapin, Matson, and Vitousek 2011" rid="ref-Chapin2011" ref-type="bibr">Chapin,
    Matson, and Vitousek 2011</xref>). So, usefulness of the concept of
    limitation depends, as one should expect, on applying it to the
    system of interest as a whole and its whole environment, rather than
    to parts within them.</p>
    <boxed-text>
    <p><bold>POSSIBLE BOX</bold></p>
    <p>explaining the watering of the desert as a change or switch of
    limitations as competitive interactions when competition by other
    species is taken into account.</p>
    </boxed-text>
    <p>One (possible?/obvious?) conclusion is that stress and strain are
    not binary conditions, as implicit already in Bidwell’s definitions.
    Both no stress and maximum stress are unusual transient situations
    and almost all plants whether growing in the field or in a
    controlled environment are in somewhere in-between situation. For
    strain, the situation is the same, because any classification of
    plant responses to environmental conditions as strain or normal
    would be in practice subjective or arbitrary in the choice of
    criteria. We next attempt to fit what we have discussed up to here
    into as description of plant and vegetation responses to stress as a
    process taking place in time and space using as starting point the
    phases “alarm”, “resistance” and “exhaustion/recovery” proposed in
    the literature.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="response-to-stress-as-a-process">
  <title>Response to stress as a process</title>
  <p>Advances in plant biology have revealed a myriad of interactive
  effects that complicate the use of traditional stress terminology. For
  example, a range of novel sensors have been identified in plants (UV-B
  and UV-A sensors, temperature sensor, salinity sensor, nitrate sensor,
  calcium sensors and so on), and these may drive adjustments of
  function in the absence of measurable strain. <italic>this could be
  expanded and citations added</italic> In the field, where plants are
  exposed to multiple correlated variables, acting both as material and
  energy resources and sources of information, plant responses can be
  complex and triggered indirectly.</p>
  <p>In addition, in the field the conditions in the environment change
  more happhazarly than in a controlled experiment, and this variation
  is what plants have adapted to. In the literature based on field
  measurements of plant’s photosynthesis, it is frequent to consider the
  conditions at some time of the day more stressful than at other times
  (e.g., cold nights, or hot and dry early afternoons).</p>
  <p>Different <italic>phases</italic> of stress have been used when
  considering individual plants, as it is where their identification
  appears less difficult. Under gradually and steadily changing
  conditions, such as is frequently the case in controlled-environment
  experiments, these phases at first sight at least, could represent a
  temporal sequence of states. In this section we consider if the idea
  of a temporal sequence of phases is applicable to “plant stress” in
  and outside the laboratory.</p>
  <sec id="the-alarm-phase">
    <title>The “alarm” phase</title>
    <p>The capacity to pre-emptively enter the alarm stage is one
    strategy among others as adaptations that avoid or resist strain
    under potentially strain-inducing conditions can be expressed either
    constitutively or conditionally in the phenotype. Conditional
    expression of traits can potentially be triggered in response to any
    condition that a plant can sense.</p>
    <p>Much of the literature on plant stress assumes that the trigger
    of the “alarm” stage is incipient stress (e.g.,
    <xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    However, this is challenged by decades of research on sensory
    ecology of plants suggesting that the most frequent triggers of
    acclimation are informational signals and cues, and that in many
    cases the alarm stage starts well before a plant is under strain but
    instead in anticipation of future potential strain (see,
    <xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>). A key consideration is that the perceived
    signal, being a source of information, only needs to be a predictor
    in the statistical sense of the future unfavourable (or favourable)
    environmental condition. Thus, the best cue or signal is provided by
    a variable that is correlated with the future potential stress and
    available well in advance of it.</p>
    <p>In plants, informational cues and signals related to likelihood
    of future potentially strain-inducing conditions are perceived
    mainly through light, temperature, chemical and turgor pressure
    receptors, although plants can also perceive gravitational,
    mechanical, magnetic and electrical cues
    (<xref alt="Karban 2015" rid="ref-Karban2015" ref-type="bibr">Karban
    2015</xref>). Downstream of the receptors a complex signal
    transduction network integrates information from multiple sources,
    regulating gene expression, metabolism, growth, and development.
    Some responses are fast, but others are delayed, such as epigenetic
    changes affecting future responses of gene expression. Some changes
    are irreversible, such as the morphology of already fully expanded
    leaves while others are more readily reversible like the readiness
    of stomata to open and close
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).</p>
    <p>The need to combine information and integrate it in time and
    space was already hinted at by Alscher and Cumming
    (<xref alt="1990" rid="ref-Alscher1990" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>)
    <italic>Alscher and Cumming (1990)</italic> when stating with
    respect to stress that “A successful survival strategy must, in some
    way, integrate external signals and induce molecular, metabolic, and
    physiological events. […] The processing of those [environmental]
    signals must involve a range of time scales and organization
    levels…”</p>
    <p>Thus, the alarm stage towards future stress is frequently
    triggered in the absence of stress or strain. Both informational
    signals and spatially and/or temporarily localized strain can
    trigger a long-lasting “alarm” stage in a whole plant, and even in
    neighboring plants
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    Furthermore, the readiness to enter the alarm stage can depend on
    maternal effects, thus indirectly on the environment experienced by
    the previous generation(s), independently of any change in the
    genome
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    In some cases, the alarm stage can be described as readiness to
    acclimate (e.g., epigenes), while in other cases as preemptive or
    anticipatory acclimation (e.g., shoot:root ratio). The alarm trigger
    is rarely binary, the intensity of the signal, its duration, the
    concurrent and earlier perception of other signals determines
    frequently the extent and nature of the subsequent acclimation
    response, i.e., the acquired information is stored, retrieved,
    combined and processed
    (<xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>).</p>
    <p>After entering the “alarm phase” an alternative phenotype starts
    being expressed. Entering the alarm stage in relation to a potential
    stressor can limit growth or yield because of the cost of
    acclimation, not necessarily as a result of strain, as acclimation
    can frequently succeed in preventing physiological strain.
    Expressing an alternative phenotype that develops over time and can
    better tolerate or escape the unfavourable conditions that are
    likely to follow, has a net cost only in case the unfavourable
    conditions fail to occur. This is so, because in the presence of the
    unfavorable condition the cost of succesful acclimation is more than
    paid back by the avoided strain-caused damage or losses.
    Anticipatory acclimation is for the “economy” of a plant similar to
    taking an insurance policy for human enterprises, and can, thus, be
    interpreted as risk management.</p>
    <p>Strain is the result of an interaction between an organism’s
    phenotype and its environment, and for any variable to be called a
    “stressor” it must disrupt an organism’s (or other biological
    system’s) function at a specific point in time. A fully acclimated
    plant will not be strained by a potential stressor, even if
    anticipatory acclimation has required a controlled reduction in its
    growth rate.</p>
    <p>To fully avoid strain, plant acclimation must precede the
    potential stressor becoming an actual stressor. A variable or
    condition becomes a stressor when it causes strain, so if strain is
    avoided by successful acclimation, the variable remains as a
    potential stressor. On the other hand, when acclimation prevents
    strain at the cost of a “controlled” decrease in growth or yield,
    the potential stressor behaves as a limitation. From this follows,
    that an informational cue or signal can also limit growth and/or
    yield.</p>
    <p><italic>POSSIBLE EXAMPLEs IN A BOX</italic> 1) red+blue LEDs used
    as only source of light for plant cultivation. 2) unnatural
    photoperiods. 3) etc.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="resistance-phase">
    <title>Resistance phase</title>
    <p>Not always acclimation is effective, sometimes the potential
    stressor(s) build up too quickly or are active for a long time and
    overwhelm a biological system. Conceptually, during the alarm phase
    “prevention” predominates and during the resistance phase “repair”
    predominates. However, the distiction between the alarm and
    resistance phases is not easy to diagnose, and conceptually
    acclimation and repair are not alternatives: they can coexist. The
    resistance phase and the alarm phase both involve active/controlled
    adjustment of function (e.g. metabolism) and morphology (e.g.,
    decrease in exposed leaf area). The distinction between acclimation
    and repair is in practice not always easy. Although repair is
    restoration of an earlier state that has been disrupted while
    acclimation the stablishment of a new state, given that plants
    develop in time, repair can be observed primarily at the cell level
    of organization, e.g., membrane permeability restored. At higher
    levels of arganization, recovery from stress is rarely, if ever,
    described as repair, e.g., replacement of leaves consumed by
    herbivores by newly formed leaves. Another consideration is that in
    this last example, new leaves in most cases will differ from the
    lost ones: the new leaves will frequently have improved defenses
    against future herbivory. Thus repair, recovery and acclimation can
    coexist. Thus classifying a response as repair or acclimation is
    difficult.</p>
    <p>Directly deciding about the “purpose” of a response as observed
    in an individual under a specific condition is philosophically
    questionable, as such a decision requires considering not only the
    realised environment but also other possible but unrealised
    conditions and their probabilities of occurrence. This is because
    “prevention” aims at mitigating future stressful conditions, that
    even if a real threat, may not be realised on the occasion we are
    studying or observing. The <italic>interpretation</italic> of
    observed plant responses is in many cases a <italic>narrative
    explanation</italic> based on function at higher levels of
    organization: photosynthetic rate interpreted as determinant of
    growth. However, this function depends concurrently on multiple
    responses at different levels of organization, which can overrride
    the causality behing the narrative explanation.</p>
    <p>In addition to repair of damage, and protection that avoids
    damage or strain, there is an additional possible strategy,
    controlled damage/destruction. This is a very frequent approach in
    engineering, e.g., most electrical systems depend on fuses to
    prevent uncontrolled damage when overloaded. In plants, the
    hypersensitive response to fungal pathogens is an example (see
    <xref alt="Wheeler 1975" rid="ref-Wheeler1975" ref-type="bibr">Wheeler
    1975</xref>). Thus, the damage we observe does not necessarily
    represent “broken machinery”, it can also represent “fuses blown as
    protection”. A fuse prevents uncontrolled damage but it clearly does
    not contribute to repairing damage or, once blown, contribute
    additional protection.</p>
    <p><italic>Possible BOX</italic> To build a narrative explanation
    about the response of a plant’s photosynthesis to the current year’s
    weather we need to consider the population the plant belongs to and
    the climate, including its variability, to which the population is
    adapted. As photosynthesis is constrained by other responses of the
    plant, the role played by photosynthesis in fitness or yield at the
    population level, cannot be considered in isolation from other
    possible concurrent responses that where limited or made possible by
    the observed change in photosynthesys under stress.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="recovery-or-exhaustion-phase">
    <title>Recovery or exhaustion phase</title>
    <p>Recovery and exhaustion phases are seen as alternatives, leading
    to two contrasting outcomes: continuing growth and reproduction and
    death, respectively. But as mentioned in the previous section, while
    damage is being repaired acclimation can continue, and stress
    tolerance enhanced. Thus recovery is possible even under continuing
    exposure to a potential stressor, that even if remaining present
    stops behaving as an active stressor because of changes in the
    plant. So transit from the resistance phase back to the alarm phase
    is also possible.</p>
    <p>Recovery involves repair of damage, but in some cases also
    compensatory responses, e.g., in partly defoliated silver birch
    sapplings the photosynthetic capacity of the remaining leaves
    increased by xx%
    (<xref alt="Ovaska et al. 1993" rid="ref-Ovaska1993" ref-type="bibr">Ovaska
    et al. 1993</xref>). However, in most cases recovery is not complete
    and fitness or yield are decreased compared to plants that have not
    been exposed to stress.</p>
    <p>Exhaustion hapens if both acclimation and repair are overwhelmed
    or innefective. A plant dies, leaves no descendence, or yields no
    commercially valuable produce. In contrast recovery can be partial
    and spans a whole range of possible outcomes.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="conditions-instead-of-phases">
    <title>Conditions instead of phases</title>
    <p>As the <italic>phases</italic> reviewed above do not represent
    necessarily a temporal sequence, we redefine them as a
    <italic>classification of transient states</italic> of the system.
    By doing this, we acknowledge that alarm state is not defined based
    on the same criterion as the other states, and that the alarm state
    can coexist in time with the other states even at the same level of
    organization.</p>
    <p>Accepting this, frees us to consider the dynamics of stress as
    dependent on two processes: 1) <italic>prevention</italic> by
    anticipated acclimation accompanied by an opportunity cost
    (<xref alt="Figure 4" rid="fig-acclimation-control-loop">Figure 4</xref>),
    and 2) <italic>repair</italic> once strain develops and results in
    damage
    (<xref alt="Figure 5" rid="fig-states-of-stress">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
    <fig id="fig-acclimation-control-loop">
      <caption><p>Figure 4: Diagram describing <italic>acclimation of an
      individual</italic> as an adjustment of the developmental strategy
      in response to cues and signals informative of likely future
      conditions in the environment.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files\figure-jats\mermaid-figure-7.png" />
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig-states-of-stress">
      <caption><p>Figure 5: Diagram describing the <italic>state of an
      individual plant</italic> based on the balance between rate of
      damage production and rate of damage repair. These states in most
      cases alternate during the course of a day and from day to day in
      a naturally fluctuating environment.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files\figure-jats\mermaid-figure-6.png" />
    </fig>
    <p>In the physiological literature it is not uncommon to consider
    damage and repair as taking place cyclically during a day, e.g.,
    UV-induced damage accumualted around noon being repaired in the
    afternoon
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>),
    or low water potential and loss of turgor in the afternoon being
    restored at night
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    Some seasonal responses such as cold hardening in perennials are
    annually recurring acclimation responses
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    A case where damage and acclimation cannot be objectively
    distinguised is the after-effect of drought on the openning response
    of stomata: stomata remain “sluggish” to open even after water
    potential and turgor have recovered
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    In some cases, readiness of stomata to open never fully recovers
    after a drought. These examples give support to describing
    <italic>states</italic> instead of <italic>phases</italic>.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="a-systems-perspective">
  <title>A systems perspective</title>
  <p>Levels of organization and hierarchical organization of systems
  play a central role in modern biological thinking
  (<xref alt="Capra and Luisi 2014" rid="ref-Capra2014" ref-type="bibr">Capra
  and Luisi 2014</xref>;
  <xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
  and Sadras 2022</xref>;
  <xref alt="Thorogood et al. 2023" rid="ref-Thorogood2023" ref-type="bibr">Thorogood
  et al. 2023</xref>) as well as the role of complexity
  (<xref alt="Capra and Luisi 2014" rid="ref-Capra2014" ref-type="bibr">Capra
  and Luisi 2014</xref>). Below we apply these ideas in an attempt to
  untangle the concepts of stress, stressor and strain as they apply to
  different levels of organization using a systems perspective. The
  systems perspective emphasizes the role of interactions and control
  loops to obtain a broader view on function and its regulation
  (<xref alt="Meadows 2015" rid="ref-Meadows2015" ref-type="bibr">Meadows
  2015</xref>).</p>
  <boxed-text>
  <p><bold>Possible box (not necessarily here)</bold></p>
  <p>Giving examples on the idea/fact that: For logical clarity the
  condition or variable being considered as a possible stressor or
  limiting factor and the biological system being considered must be
  observed at the same temporal and spatial scales. It also follows that
  conclusions unless explicitly and formally upscaled or downscaled
  using a system’s perspective do not necessarily apply at levels above
  or below the one studied.</p>
  <p>Should we cite the Spandrels’ paper?</p>
  </boxed-text>
  <sec id="the-individual">
    <title>The individual</title>
    <p>As discussed in previous sections, potential and actual stressors
    in nature are rarely single environmental factors but instead
    combinations of factors acting jointly or sequentially. Information
    acquired by plants through the perception of cues and signals in the
    environment is combined during transduction (e.g.,
    <xref alt="Rai, Morales, and Aphalo 2021" rid="ref-Rai2021" ref-type="bibr">Rai,
    Morales, and Aphalo 2021</xref>;
    <xref alt="Podolec, Demarsy, and Ulm 2021" rid="ref-Podolec2021a" ref-type="bibr">Podolec,
    Demarsy, and Ulm 2021</xref>;
    <xref alt="Sellaro et al. 2024" rid="ref-Sellaro2024" ref-type="bibr">Sellaro
    et al. 2024</xref>;
    <xref alt="Casal and Qüesta 2018" rid="ref-Casal2018" ref-type="bibr">Casal
    and Qüesta 2018</xref>). Acquired information and experienced stress
    drastically affects future responses to both informational cues and
    signals, and to potential stressors thanks to enhanced readiness to
    respond and actually implemented physiological, morphological and
    developmental acclimation
    (<xref alt="Falik, Mauda, and Novoplansky 2024" rid="ref-Falik2024" ref-type="bibr">Falik,
    Mauda, and Novoplansky 2024</xref>). Acclimation is in itself a
    syndrome of delicately orchestrated and coordinated concurrent
    responses of physiology, morphology and development. This is because
    the contributions of most physiological, morphological and
    developmental responses to fitness are interrrelated, e.g., water
    use, water transport, water storage, and water uptake must be in
    balance with each other, and building each of these capacities
    requires photosynthates and mineral nutrients from shared pools.
    Furthermore, water use is linked to photosynthesis by stomatal
    conductance, while the rate of photosynthesis feeds back into the
    pool of photosynthates. Any change in light interception, e.g.,
    changes in the area of leaves, angle of display of leaves, white
    pubescence or wax deposits on the epidermis, etc., affect both
    transpiration and photosynthesis, but not equally. An increase in
    root to shoot dry mass ratio will favour not only water uptake but
    also the uptake of mineral nutrients. The regulation of
    photosynthesis takes place across levels of organization from
    proteins in thylacoid membranes of chloroplasts to leaf movements
    (<xref alt="Shevela, Björn, and Govindjee 2019" rid="ref-Shevela2019" ref-type="bibr">Shevela,
    Björn, and Govindjee 2019</xref>).</p>
    <p>The more we learn about the molecular and physiological
    mechanisms relevant to stress, the more intractable the problem of
    upscaling from these levels to levels relevant to fitness and yield
    appears. One difficulty, we think, is attempting to force this
    knowledge into two boxes by assuming that stress is distinct from
    normal, i.e., that there is a clear dichotomy. The two extreme
    conditions are exceptional. Realization of potential fitness or crop
    yield is almost never fully achieved in practice and death leaving
    no offspring rather infrequent in plants. In the case of
    populations, complete extinction is even less frequent. Most
    individual plants and populations function somewhere between these
    limits. So, if we take optimal conditions as a reference, we can
    conclude that nearly all plants are strained. In contrast, if we
    define strain as a terminal disruption leading to premature plant
    death or no offspring, we can conclude that strain is an exceptional
    condition. Both of these views, fail to recognize that intermediate
    degrees of strain and the gradient between the extreme situations
    and its dynamics in time and space are the most interesting.</p>
    <p>Time and its progression are important, as fitness is achieved
    through an individual’s life time, and in annual plants achieved
    only towards the end of the life cycle. As growth and development
    progresses, the remaining available routes for plasticity decrease,
    and this forces a change in strategy as a plant develops
    (<xref alt="H. Shemesh and Novoplansky 2013" rid="ref-Shemesh2013" ref-type="bibr">H.
    Shemesh and Novoplansky 2013</xref>). This decreasing ability for
    acclimation concurrent with development and growth, can make
    successful anticipation and early “decision making” highly
    beneficial to fitness.</p>
    <p>From a mechanistic perspective, we may ask, is physiology
    fundamentally different in the presence and absence of strain?
    Strain in a plant is the result of an interaction, so it is not a
    state dependent only on the environment or on the plant phenotype.
    We think that it is most productive to think in terms of a
    regulation system that gradually adjusts plants’ plastic “behavior”
    to avoid or tolerate strain. This is like a navigation system,
    trying to avoid a crash and most of the time succeeding. The control
    system may engage in an emergency state of enhanced alertness in a
    crisis, but this can be interpreted as an effort to modify a set
    point in a control system, rather than as switch between two
    distinct system states.</p>
    <p>As with many other things in biology, hierarchical, thus
    asymmetrical, organization of living systems precludes use of direct
    extrapolation for upscaling and downscaling of stressed states
    (<xref alt="Noble 2012" rid="ref-Noble2012" ref-type="bibr">Noble
    2012</xref>,
    <xref alt="2017" rid="ref-Noble2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>;
    <xref alt="Passioura 2010" rid="ref-Passioura2010" ref-type="bibr">Passioura
    2010</xref>,
    <xref alt="2020" rid="ref-Passioura2020" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).
    This is a feature of biological systems that affects all definitions
    of stress, stressor and strain. Thus we need to be aware that signs
    of metabolic and physiological strain (sensu Levitt) cannot be
    directly used to characterize whole-organism, in our case,
    whole-plant strain. Similarly, signs of strain at individual plant
    level cannot be directly used to assess strain at farm plot or
    ecosystem levels.</p>
    <p>Currently, upscaling from gene expression and physiology in
    controlled environment studies to the behavior of plant populations
    and communities in the field is impeded by a poor (lack of?)
    understanding of the links among regulatory mechanisms at different
    levels of organization. At each level of organization, both sharing
    of and competition for resources and information can take place.
    Information and resources move both upwards and downwards across the
    (rather arbitrary?) boundaries between levels of organization. As
    these processes can contribute to fitness, they have been selected
    during evolution and/or crop breeding, and are thus a fundamental
    component of biological systems.</p>
    <boxed-text>
    <p><bold>Describing complexity</bold></p>
    <p>A possible classification of problems for modelling has three
    categories: systems of small numbers, systems of large numbers and
    systems in-between these extremes
    (<xref alt="XXXX?" rid="ref-XXXX" ref-type="bibr"><bold>XXXX?</bold></xref>).
    With systems of a small number of diferent agents and of possible
    interactions we can describe individual interactions between agents,
    e.g., competition between a pair of individual plants. With large
    numbers of agents and an even larger number of interactions among
    them, a probabilistic or statistical approach is most effective when
    the agents can be described as a population, e.g., allele
    frequencies in in population. Most real systems are more complex,
    with interactions taking place among agents belonging to different
    populations and a heirarchical organization with nesting of agents.
    In such cases a detailed description of all significant interactions
    and hierachical relationships is impractical or even impossible. A
    systems approach attemps to describe only the most important
    interactions ang hierarchies among agents to achieve a simplified
    description that can provide an approximate explaination of the
    behaviour of the described system under <italic>a subset of the
    possible conditions in its environment</italic>.</p>
    <p>We may ask if the currently in fashion large language models
    could provide a solution. It is important to be aware that the aim
    of these models is only prediction, not estimation or attribution of
    the observed responses to causes or mechanisms
    (<xref alt="Efron 2020" rid="ref-Efron2020" ref-type="bibr">Efron
    2020</xref>). They can be tought of as huge regression models not
    more informative than a polynomial regression. We come back round to
    what we discussed in relation to the possible triggers for
    anticipatory acclimation: a good predictor needs only be a good
    source of information. As with any purely empirical regression such
    large models can predict behaviours within the scope of the data
    used to train them, and given their extreme complexity cannot
    provide insights on the underlying mechanisms active in the real
    system. So, even if these models help with prediction, they do not
    provide mechanistic insights or directly contribute to improved
    understanding. On the other hand atificial-intelligence-based
    approaches can with tasks such as extraction of data from images,
    discovery of patterns in data and similar tasks that facilitate the
    research process.</p>
    </boxed-text>
    <p>We think that insufficient awareness about the difficulties of
    scaling up has been a major source of confusion in stress
    physiology, especially in attempts to transfer conclusions from
    short-term studies under controlled environments to applications
    under field conditions sometimes leading to inaccurate conclusions
    about whole-plant’s strain based on metabolic and cell level assays
    of strain (the result of localized stress) or on their possible
    impact on produce yield or quality.</p>
    <p>At different levels of organization it is natural to asses
    performance based on different variables, using different spatial
    and time scales. Performance at levels of organization within the
    organism is related to control mechanisms at metabolic, cell and
    organ levels. Failure of such systems to control a given low level
    function does not necessarily result in decreased performance at
    higher levels of organization and/or at longer time scales. We may
    define, for example, “strain” at tissue or cell levels based on an
    ineffective quenching of ROS, which may trigger at whole plant level
    a response that is inconsequential or either increases or decreases
    plant fitness or yield. Especially when such metabolic disturbances
    are transient, they may function as informational signals at the
    whole organism level triggering enhanced fitness compared to their
    absence. If we move upwards from individual plants to populations
    and communities, especially in natural populations with heterogenous
    genotypes, we face a similar challenge. To mechanistically upscale
    the behaviour of plants we need to understand in detail plant-plant
    interactions involving resources but also those related information,
    both signals used for plant-plant communication as well as cues
    derived from neighboring plant responses.</p>
    <boxed-text>
    <p><bold>Crop breeding and upscaling (Possible BOX)</bold></p>
    <p>The analysis presented here shows that natural-selection- and
    breeding-selection as reference together with a scaling approach
    that incorporates the hierarchical structure of biological systems
    can avoid many of the weaknesses of the ill-defined concepts and
    terminology frequently used to describe biological stress in plants.
    In this box we describe how it applies to crop breeding for stress
    tolerance.</p>
    <p>For example, a crop breeder is ultimately interested in yield,
    and aims at reducing strain quantified based on yield. To a breeder
    biological strain assessed based on fitness is irrelevant while it
    can be the main interest on an ecologist. Both, breeder and
    ecologist, maybe interested in strain as well as in acclimation at
    cellular level, but only in relation to their contributions to
    responses at the higher levels of organization, quantified using the
    measures of performance they are interested in.</p>
    <p>As Alscher and Cumming
    (<xref alt="1990" rid="ref-Alscher1990" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>)
    Alscher and Cumming (1990) wrote, “…it is quite obvious that
    information obtained from molecular and biochemical
    characterizations of plant stress cannot legitimately be applied to
    whole organisms directly and certainly not to organisms growing in
    the field.” We hope our attempt at summarizing, organizing and
    connecting different definitions of stress, will contribute to the
    realization of the integration across disciplines that Alscher and
    Cumming
    (<xref alt="1990" rid="ref-Alscher1990" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>)
    already envisaged three decades ago and the book edited by
    (<xref alt="J. A. C. Smith and Griffiths 1993" rid="ref-Smith1993a" ref-type="bibr">J.
    A. C. Smith and Griffiths 1993</xref>) attempted in relation to
    water stress.</p>
    <p>From a mechanistic perspective, we may ask, is physiology
    fundamentally different in the presence and absence of strain?
    Strain is the result of an interaction, so it is not a state of the
    environment or a state of the plant. We think that it is most
    productive to think in terms of a regulation system that gradually
    adjusts plants’ plastic “behavior” to avoid or tolerate strain. This
    is like a navigation system, trying to avoid a crash and most of the
    time succeeding. The control system may engage in an emergency state
    of enhanced alertness in a crisis, but this can be interpreted as a
    shift in a set point of a control system, rather than as a distinct
    system.</p>
    </boxed-text>
    <p>Views vary on whether stress is to be considered a normal, even
    necessary condition for development
    (<xref alt="Badyaev et al. 2015" rid="ref-Badyaev2015" ref-type="bibr">Badyaev
    et al. 2015</xref>, and refs. therein), or as an exceptional
    condition with mainly negative consequences
    (<xref alt="Jansen and Potters 2017" rid="ref-Jansen2017" ref-type="bibr">Jansen
    and Potters 2017</xref>). In part this relates to levels of
    organization and the need to distinguish between metabolic-, cell-,
    organ-, individual- or even population-level challenges to
    performance including its dependence on “decision making” (sensu
    <xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>). Furthermore, homeostasis at each of these
    levels works at different spatial and temporal scales. The word
    stress is used also at even higher levels of organization,
    communities, ecosystems, and the biosphere. At these higher levels
    of organization stability and resilience are emergent properties of
    very complex systems, with natural selection indirectly affecting
    them
    (<xref alt="Godfrey-Smith 2009" rid="ref-GodfreySmith2009" ref-type="bibr">Godfrey-Smith
    2009</xref>;
    <xref alt="Thorogood et al. 2023" rid="ref-Thorogood2023" ref-type="bibr">Thorogood
    et al. 2023</xref>).</p>
    <p>It is relevant to consider how the concepts of eustress and
    distress (see
    <xref alt="Jansen and Potters 2017" rid="ref-Jansen2017" ref-type="bibr">Jansen
    and Potters 2017</xref>) can be interpreted from a hierarchical
    viewpoint. Körner
    (<xref alt="2018" rid="ref-Koerner2018" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)
    writes “Levitt (1960) has distinguished between conditioning stress
    or ‘eustress’, which, despite it being potentially harmful for some
    individuals, it increases the long-term fitness of a species, and
    ‘distress’, conditions in which environmental constraints become
    increasingly destructive.” While Levitt considered individuals and
    species, two levels of organization, an equivalent hierarchical
    relationship exists between cells or tissues and whole plants. For a
    plant, fitness is the relevant measure of performance , and stress
    on cells, tissues or organs can increase (eustress), decrease
    (distress) or be inconsequential for the plant as a whole.</p>
    <p>Eustress triggers adaptive acclimation, while distress disrupts
    homeostasis or triggers mal-adaptive responses, at the plant level
    of organization. So more broadly, distress can be stress on lower
    levels of organization that induces stress at a higher level of
    organization and eustress can be stress that either takes place at
    lower levels of organization and/or is transient and that helps
    mitigate or avoid strain, or even enhance performance, at higher
    levels of organization or over the lifetime of an organism. Jansen
    and Potters
    (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-Jansen2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)
    consider the strength of the stress as the determinant of it
    behaving as eustress or distress. However, as discussed above stress
    is not a property inherent to the stressor but instead determined by
    the character of the plant’s response, in other words, stress, as
    well as eustress and distress are emergent properties originating
    from the interaction between a plant and its environment during a
    time period relevant to the measure of performance of interest. When
    Badyaev et al.
    (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-Badyaev2015" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>)
    consider stress as a normal, even necessary condition for normal
    development in animals, they imply that stress at a short temporal
    scale is needed for a normal development observed at a longer time
    scale and lifetime fitness. The propagation of a strain event
    defines distress, while acclimation triggered by a transient strain
    event that ameliorates or avoids later stress events and, thus,
    enhances fitness defines eustress (Fig. 1).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="selection-of-stress-tolerance">
    <title>Selection of stress tolerance</title>
    <p>Traits associated with stress resistance (e.g. avoidance or
    tolerance) have arisen as a result of exposure and selection under
    potential stress-inducing conditions during previous generations,
    and this process is reflected in the plant genome. At the population
    level, this process comprises directional selection, appearance of
    novel traits but also potentially local extinction
    (<xref alt="Badyaev 2005" rid="ref-Badyaev2005" ref-type="bibr">Badyaev
    2005</xref>), (acute) stress events play an important role in
    evolution. From an evolutionary viewpoint, stress is a condition
    compromising reproduction and survival, from which it might be
    concluded that plants are very seldom under stress in their natural
    environment, i.e. such plants are either adapted to, or extinct in
    that environment. However, while this simplification may be
    theoretically correct in the case of some extreme (life or death)
    stress-conditions, it does not apply to more realistic “transient”
    and/or “quantitative” stress conditions where a balance between
    stress resistance and associated fitness cost (trade-off) will
    determine survival as well as performance measured as fitness.
    However, the hypothetical exposure to “life or death” stress
    conditions provides a key insight by highlighting that stress at
    individual or population (but not necessarily physiological) level
    can be defined as the result of lack of adaptation or
    miss-adaptation to a specific condition. Then, at two levels of
    organization, individual and population, we can dispense with
    definitions of stress based on disruption of physiology and/or
    homeostasis. This view is consistent with Körner
    (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-Koerner2003" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>),
    who writes “Stressed plants are commonly those which are unfit for a
    given situation…”. As the latter plants will be impaired in their
    reproduction, they can be assumed to go locally extinct, leading
    Körner
    (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-Koerner2003" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>)
    to state that “Stressful environments hardly exist”.</p>
    <p>Second, numerous studies have documented an increase in
    phenotypic and genotypic variance under stress, and it is suggested
    that this variance is a source of novel adaptations under changed
    environments (XXX).</p>
    <p>Yet, for stress-induced modifications to have evolutionary
    importance they have to be inherited and persist in a sufficient
    number of individuals within a population. This requires individuals
    with altered genotypes to survive stress and reproduce; thus
    stress-induced variation has to be accommodated by an organism
    without drastically reducing its functionality.”</p>
    <p>Plasticity itself, is under both natural selection and plastic
    regulation (metaplasticity sensu
    <xref alt="Ariel Novoplansky 2009" rid="ref-Novoplansky2009" ref-type="bibr">Ariel
    Novoplansky 2009</xref>). Anticipatory or pre-emptive acclimation is
    crucial for fitness, as demonstrated by phenological research in
    many plant species (e.g.,
    <xref alt="Hänninen 2016" rid="ref-Hanninen2016" ref-type="bibr">Hänninen
    2016</xref>) as well as research on competition for light and shade
    avoidance
    (<xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>;
    <xref alt="Sellaro et al. 2024" rid="ref-Sellaro2024" ref-type="bibr">Sellaro
    et al. 2024</xref>). It is also important to keep in mind that
    extreme stress events, that repeat at very long-time intervals can
    select for “risk avoidance” behavior
    (<xref alt="H. Shemesh and Novoplansky 2013" rid="ref-Shemesh2013" ref-type="bibr">H.
    Shemesh and Novoplansky 2013</xref>), thus, what may appear as
    suboptimal behavior in the short term, maybe beneficial on a longer
    time scale by ensuring the survival of the population.</p>
    <p>A central question in stress biology is how organisms can prepare
    for exposure to extreme environmental change? It can be argued that
    the organism’s ability to mount an appropriate reaction to a
    stressor requires (advance/early) recognition and evaluation of the
    risks and limitations imposed by a likelihood of exposure to an
    extreme environment in the future. Mechanistically, the
    physiological consequences of exposure to the environment determine
    the necessary “countermeasures”. In turn, this raises the question
    about the role in plants of “recollections” of having been exposed
    to a stressor, or to cues and signals of its high likelihood, on an
    earlier occasion. Distinct from traditional evolutionary
    perspectives, new breakthroughs have been made in characterizing
    plant “memory” within the current generation, and in some cases
    recent past generations, as reflected in the epigenome and phenome
    (<xref alt="Yan et al. 2020" rid="ref-Yan2020" ref-type="bibr">Yan
    et al. 2020</xref>;
    <xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
    and Sadras 2022</xref>).</p>
    <p>Badyaev
    (<xref alt="2005" rid="ref-Badyaev2005" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>)
    contends that “The response to stress depends crucially on prior
    experience and a ‘memory’ of response to a stressor. Generally,
    repeated exposure to a particular stressor favors the evolution of
    mechanisms that suppress an organism-wide stress reaction and,
    instead, activate stress-specific responses”. We can think of these
    responses as being pre-emptive, and triggered in advance of stress,
    or palliative and triggered by, possibly incipient, stress. As
    discussed by Aphalo and Sadras
    (<xref alt="2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>)
    pre-emptive acclimation can be triggered by sensing of cues (see
    section XXX) and/or signals in the environment probabilistically
    correlated with high likelihood of future exposure to a potential
    stressor. The putative future stressor variables or conditions can
    also behave as informational cues before they become stressors.
    Thus, this creates a novel stress perspective, with important
    consequences for “stress concepts”. Rather, than the “traditional”
    (<xref alt="xxxx?" rid="ref-xxxx" ref-type="bibr"><bold>xxxx?</bold></xref>)
    perspective whereby mainly strain in individual cells, tissues or
    organs gives rise to signals, such as the release of hormones or
    ROS, that convey information to other parts of the plant that
    subsequently respond in ways that contribute to whole-plant fitness,
    there is an additional pre-emptive adaptive response which decouples
    “adaptive stress-responses” from actual strain.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusions">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Stress is an abstract concept describing the consequences of a
  deviation away from a “normal” (or alternatively “target”) state of a
  biological system. In practice, stress is used to describe a whole set
  of conditions that have in common some properties but can differ in
  others, including their causes, mechanisms and consequences. Stress is
  a generic concept, like fruit in Botany, that includes not only fruits
  from different plant species, but also different types of fruits such
  as accorns, drupes, grains, etc.</p>
  <p>Even statements like “plants are under drought stress” or “… under
  heat stress” specify only the cause, not the mechanism or the
  consequences or type of strain triggered. “Oxidative stress in
  mesophyll cells triggered by prolonged exposure to high temperature
  and strong light” starts to narrow down into a small set of conditions
  and consequences, still dependent on the exact temperature, spectral
  irradiance, exposure time and plant phenotype and genotype.</p>
  <p>Even as an abstraction, “stress” is used by different researchers
  from different perspectives, mostly dependent on the level of
  organization and type of function being described. Like the term
  “fruit”, the terms “stress”, “stressor” and “strain” are extremely
  useful in describing generalities about stress, but are too ambiguous
  to be used unqualified when describing specific cases.</p>
  <p>A stressor is a stressor, by definition, only as a result of an
  organism’s responses, rather than intrinsically. An organism’s
  responses to the environment are adaptive or not depending on the
  context where they are triggered in, i.e., most responses of organisms
  are not inherently favorable or negative. Their contribution to
  fitness or crop yield are circimstantial.</p>
  <p>The difference between “eustress” and “distress” is one of
  valuation: eustress is a good stress while distress is a bad stress.
  The mechanisms do not necessarily differ, and the same stress event
  can be labeled as eustress or distress if evaluted at different points
  in time or using different criteria. As a binary classification based
  on a continuous valuation scale it represents an oversimplification
  prone to hide nuances. On the positive side, it makes clear that “bad”
  stress observed at one point in time can be beneficial at a later
  time, and that stress at a lower level of organization can be
  beneficial at higher levels of organization.</p>
  <p>A major diference exists between natural and managed biological
  systems. When studying a natural system we attempt to infer the normal
  condition based on our knowledge of the functioning of the system.
  There is a danger of being arbitrary or teleological in this
  inference, but we look at the system from a holistic perspective and
  as objectively as possible. In this case we can conclude that
  biological stress makes sense in the light of evolution and
  environmental change. In managed systems, the target is that set by
  the human manager, and it can be even an economic one. This is an
  utilitarian perspective on stress and its use makes sense only for
  human enterprises.</p>
  <p>As Körner
  (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-Koerner2003" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>)
  emphasizes, it is crucial not to apply a utilitarian definition of
  stress in ecology. For example, a crop breeder is ultimately
  interested in yield, and aims at reducing strain quantified based on
  yield. To a breeder biological strain assessed based on fitness can be
  irrelevant while it can be the main interest for an ecologist. Both
  breeder and ecologist, maybe interested in strain at cellular level,
  but only in relation to its contribution to responses at higher levels
  of organization. In this case, breakdown of strict physiological
  homeostasis is not the correct criterion to use for defining plant,
  population or crop stress.</p>
  <p>A given response to a given informational signal can make a
  positive or negative contribution to fitness depending on future, yet
  to be realized, environmental conditions. Furthermore, at the time of
  response, these future environmental conditions cannot be predicted
  with certainty, at best they can be assigned a probability of being
  realized at a future time.</p>
  <p>Responses mediated by sensory mechanisms responsive to the external
  environment and those triggered by the state of metabolism are not
  necessarily as different as they initially appear. In most cases,
  responses to the state of metabolism, and even to damage, also involve
  sensors responsive to the internal environment of the cell and
  signaling triggering adjustments in regulatory mechanisms and gene
  expression.</p>
  <p>When considering populations growing in a heterogenous environment,
  their performance integrates the responses of individuals and the
  variation in the environment. Different individuals may have different
  genotypes and individuals of the same genotype will express different
  phenotypes based on the local environment they are exposed to.
  Exploitation of small-scale environmental variation relies on
  phenotypic plasticity (see
  <xref alt="Grime 1994" rid="ref-Grime1994" ref-type="bibr">Grime
  1994</xref>).</p>
  <p>A further distinction is important: acclimation describes responses
  that have been realized (implemented), while memory, describes changes
  is the readiness to respond or the nature of a future response to a
  specific stimulus or a combination of stimuli
  (<xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
  and Sadras 2022</xref>). This distinction is important from the
  viewpoint of investment of resources: Acclimation consumes resources
  while memory modifies the “rules” applicable to future “decisions”
  about the use of resources. Plasticity is a more abstract concept,
  describing the hability to express different phenotypes from the same
  genotype, irrespective of mechanisms (<italic>IS THIS
  CORRECT?</italic>).</p>
  <p>Any response, independently of the mechanism that triggers it, can
  have both immediate and/or delayed consequences relevant to fitness.
  We consider those responses that have a delayed favorable effect on
  fitness as leading to anticipatory acclimation. The same response can
  have an immediate effect in addition to contributing to acclimation.
  Acclimation can also be pre-emptive or triggered by proxies correlated
  with a given environmental challenge or bounty
  (<xref alt="Aphalo and Sadras 2022" rid="ref-Aphalo2022" ref-type="bibr">Aphalo
  and Sadras 2022</xref>). Given the variability of the environment in
  time and space and the variation in the genotype, epigenome and
  phenotype of the members of a population of plants, wild or
  cultivated, statistical probabilities are involved. The ability to
  thrive in a variable and ever changing environment is selected for as
  a direct consequence of the existence of variability in the
  environment where selection takes place.</p>
  <p>In nature, stress will rarely cause a disruption such that all
  regulation is rendered ineffective, and almost never acclimation based
  on the sensing of non-stress conditions will be inconsequential to
  performance under subsequent stress conditions. Both strain and
  acclimation are quantitative traits and mechanistically syndromes.
  Thus, neither stress nor acclimation are binary responses, they have
  to be described and measured as continuous. A no stress condition is
  in most cases a fiction, in nature almost always there will be
  deviations from the normal, and deviations can exist at any level of
  organization.</p>
  <p>Levels of organization and temporal and spatial scale all play
  crucial roles in biology, from biochemistry all the way up to ecology
  and evolution
  (<xref alt="Godfrey-Smith 2009" rid="ref-GodfreySmith2009" ref-type="bibr">Godfrey-Smith
  2009</xref>;
  <xref alt="Capra and Luisi 2014" rid="ref-Capra2014" ref-type="bibr">Capra
  and Luisi 2014</xref>). The multiple feedback loops and interactions
  inherent to all living systems give rise to difficult-to-predict
  emergent properties and behavior at higher levels of organization. So,
  it is necessary not to confuse stress at the cellular level with
  stress at whole-plant level or stress at whole-plant level with stress
  at population level or crop field level. Upscaling of “stress” is
  difficult, and frequently even counterintuitive.</p>
  <p>From an actionable perspective, as stress-triggered responses have
  much in common to anticipatory responses and to constitutive traits
  affording stress tolerance and stressors are not inherently different
  to other environmental conditions, shouldn’t we simply integrate all
  research on responses to environmental variability under the same
  umbrella? Even if this is the case, unambiguous definitions for
  limitation, stress, stressor and strain that fulfil the requirements
  of epistemic metaphors (sensu
  <xref alt="Palma 2016" rid="ref-Palma2016" ref-type="bibr">Palma
  2016</xref>) are needed. These terms describe abstract concepts that
  need to be carefully qualified when used to describe specific cases or
  situations. Otherwise, ambiguities and apparent contradictions are
  generated in the scientific discourse.</p>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
<ref-list>
  <title></title>
  <ref id="ref-Zeiger1970">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Zeiger</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>System theoretic analysis of models: Computer simulation of a living cell</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1970">1970</year>
      <volume>29</volume>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-5193(70)90117-7</pub-id>
      <fpage>35</fpage>
      <lpage>56</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Selye1975">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Selye</surname><given-names>Hans</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Confusion and controversy in the stress field</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Human Stress</source>
      <publisher-name>Informa UK Limited</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1975-06">1975</year><month>06</month>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0097840x.1975.9940406</pub-id>
      <fpage>37</fpage>
      <lpage>44</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-WestEberhard2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>West-Eberhard</surname><given-names>Mary Jane</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Modularity as a universal emergent property of biological traits</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Experimental Zoology Part B: Molecular and Developmental Evolution</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-11">2019</year><month>11</month>
      <volume>332</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jez.b.22913</pub-id>
      <fpage>356</fpage>
      <lpage>364</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Hanninen2016">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Hänninen</surname><given-names>Heikki</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Boreal and temperate trees in a changing climate</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
      <isbn>9789401795258</isbn>
      <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-94-017-7549-6</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-017-7549-6</pub-id>
      <fpage>x + 210</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Trewavas1986">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Trewavas</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Introduction</article-title>
      <source>Plasticity in plants</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Trewavas</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>The Company of Biologists</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1986">1986</year>
      <isbn>0-948601-03-5</isbn>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>4</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Whitehead1963">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The effects of exposure on growth and development</article-title>
      <source>The water relations of plants</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1963">1963</year>
      <fpage>235</fpage>
      <lpage>245</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Bidwell1979">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bidwell</surname><given-names>Roger G. S.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant physiology</source>
      <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1979">1979</year>
      <edition>2</edition>
      <isbn>0023094303</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Highkin1960">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Highkin</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The effect of constant temperature environments and of continuous light on the growth and development of pea plants</article-title>
      <source>Cold Spring Harbor Symposia on Quantitative Biology</source>
      <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1960-01">1960</year><month>01</month>
      <volume>25</volume>
      <issue>0</issue>
      <issn>1943-4456</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/sqb.1960.025.01.023</pub-id>
      <fpage>231</fpage>
      <lpage>238</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Shemesh2010">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Shemesh</surname><given-names>Hagai</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Arbiv</surname><given-names>Adi</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Gersani</surname><given-names>Mordechai</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ovadia</surname><given-names>Ofer</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Novoplansky</surname><given-names>Ariel</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Anticipating future conditions via trajectory sensitivity.</article-title>
      <source>Plant signaling &amp; behavior</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Bruun</surname><given-names>Hans Henrik</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <issue>11</issue>
      <issn>1559-2324</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0010824</pub-id>
      <fpage>1501</fpage>
      <lpage>1503</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Holopainen2010">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Holopainen</surname><given-names>Jarmo K.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Multiple stress factors and the emission of plant VOCs</article-title>
      <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2010-03">2010</year><month>03</month>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2010.01.006</pub-id>
      <fpage>176</fpage>
      <lpage>184</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Pierik2014">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Pierik</surname><given-names>Ronald</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ballaré</surname><given-names>Carlos L</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>Marcel</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Ecology of plant volatiles: Taking a plant community perspective.</article-title>
      <source>Plant, cell &amp; environment</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
      <volume>37</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.12330</pub-id>
      <fpage>1845</fpage>
      <lpage>1853</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Simpraga2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Šimpraga</surname><given-names>Maja</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ghimire</surname><given-names>Rajendra P.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Straeten</surname><given-names>Dominique Van Der</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Blande</surname><given-names>James D.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kasurinen</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sorvari</surname><given-names>Jouni</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Holopainen</surname><given-names>Toini</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Adriaenssens</surname><given-names>Sandy</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Holopainen</surname><given-names>Jarmo K.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kivimäenpää</surname><given-names>Minna</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Unravelling the functions of biogenic volatiles in boreal and temperate forest ecosystems</article-title>
      <source>European Journal of Forest Research</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer Science; Business Media LLC</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-07">2019</year><month>07</month>
      <volume>138</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10342-019-01213-2</pub-id>
      <fpage>763</fpage>
      <lpage>787</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Falik2011">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Falik</surname><given-names>Omer</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mordoch</surname><given-names>Yonat</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Quansah</surname><given-names>Lydia</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Fait</surname><given-names>Aaron</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Novoplansky</surname><given-names>Ariel</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Rumor has it...: Relay communication of stress cues in plants</article-title>
      <source>PLoS ONE</source>
      <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>11</issue>
      <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0023625</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023625</pub-id>
      <fpage>e23625</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-GodfreySmith2014">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Godfrey-Smith</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Philosophy of biology</source>
      <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
      <isbn>9781400850440</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Grime1994">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Grime</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The role of plasticity in exploiting environmental heterogeneity</article-title>
      <source>Exploitation of environmental heterogeneity by plants: Ecophysiological processes above- and belowground</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Pearcy</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/b978-0-12-155070-7.50006-8</pub-id>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>19</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Noble2012">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>Denis</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A theory of biological relativity: No privileged level of causation</article-title>
      <source>Interface Focus</source>
      <publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2012-11">2012</year><month>11</month>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsfs.2011.0067</pub-id>
      <fpage>55</fpage>
      <lpage>64</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Sinclair2012">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>Thomas R.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Rufty</surname><given-names>Thomas W.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Nitrogen and water resources commonly limit crop yield increases, not necessarily plant genetics</article-title>
      <source>Global Food Security</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2012-12">2012</year><month>12</month>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gfs.2012.07.001</pub-id>
      <fpage>94</fpage>
      <lpage>98</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-WestEberhard2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>West-Eberhard</surname><given-names>Mary Jane</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Modularity as a universal emergent property of biological traits</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Experimental Zoology Part B: Molecular and Developmental Evolution</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-11">2019</year><month>11</month>
      <volume>332</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jez.b.22913</pub-id>
      <fpage>356</fpage>
      <lpage>364</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Huey2002">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Plants versus animals: Do they deal with stress in different ways?</article-title>
      <source>Integrative and Comparative Biology</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2002-07">2002</year><month>07</month>
      <volume>42</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icb/42.3.415</pub-id>
      <fpage>415</fpage>
      <lpage>423</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Molins2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Molins</surname><given-names>Francisco</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>Miguel Ángel</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Alacreu-Crespo</surname><given-names>Adrian</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Early stages of the acute physical stress response increase loss aversion and learning on decision making: A bayesian approach</article-title>
      <source>Physiology &amp; Behavior</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021-08">2021</year><month>08</month>
      <volume>237</volume>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physbeh.2021.113459</pub-id>
      <fpage>113459</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Noble2017">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>Denis</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Evolution viewed from physics, physiology and medicine</article-title>
      <source>Interface Focus</source>
      <publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017-08">2017</year><month>08</month>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsfs.2016.0159</pub-id>
      <fpage>20160159</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Passioura2010">
    <element-citation>
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Passioura</surname><given-names>John B.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Plant-water relations</article-title>
      <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2010-02">2010</year><month>02</month>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9780470015902.a0001288.pub2</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Koerner2018">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Körner</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Concepts in empirical plant ecology</article-title>
      <source>Plant Ecology &amp; Diversity</source>
      <publisher-name>Informa UK Limited</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2018-07">2018</year><month>07</month>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17550874.2018.1540021</pub-id>
      <fpage>405</fpage>
      <lpage>428</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Falik2022">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Falik</surname><given-names>Omer</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mauda</surname><given-names>Shachar</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Novoplansky</surname><given-names>Ariel</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The ecological implications of interplant drought cuing</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Ecology</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2022-09">2022</year><month>09</month>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2745.13991</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Keddy2017">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Keddy</surname><given-names>Paul A.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant ecology</source>
      <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017-04-17">2017</year><month>04</month><day>17</day>
      <isbn>1107114233</isbn>
      <uri>http://www.ebook.de/de/product/26311639/paul_a_keddy_plant_ecology.html</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Palma2016">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>Hector</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Ciencia y metaforas. Critica de una razon incestuosa</source>
      <publisher-name>Prometeo Libros</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
      <isbn>9789875747562</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Pye1995">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Pye</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The nature and art of workmanship</source>
      <publisher-name>Herbert Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
      <edition>Revised ed., repr.</edition>
      <isbn>9780713689310</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Niklas1994">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Niklas</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant allometry: The scalling of plant form and process</source>
      <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Passioura2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Passioura</surname><given-names>John B.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Translational research in agriculture. Can we do it better?</article-title>
      <source>Crop and Pasture Science</source>
      <publisher-name>CSIRO Publishing</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <volume>71</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/cp20066</pub-id>
      <fpage>517</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Smith1993a">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. A. C.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Water deficits: Plant responses from cell to community</source>
      <publisher-name>Bios Scientific Publishers</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year>
      <fpage>345</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Thorogood2023">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Thorogood</surname><given-names>Rose</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mustonen</surname><given-names>Ville</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Aleixo</surname><given-names>Alexandre</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Aphalo</surname><given-names>Pedro J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Asiegbu</surname><given-names>Fred O.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Cabeza</surname><given-names>Mar</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Candolin</surname><given-names>Ulrika</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>Pedro</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Eronen</surname><given-names>Jussi T.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Hällfors</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Hovatta</surname><given-names>Iiris</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Juslén</surname><given-names>Aino</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kovalchuk</surname><given-names>Andriy</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kulmuni</surname><given-names>Jonna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kuula</surname><given-names>Liisa</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mäkipää</surname><given-names>Raisa</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ovaskainen</surname><given-names>Otso</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Pesonen</surname><given-names>Anu-Katriina</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Primmer</surname><given-names>Craig R.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Saastamoinen</surname><given-names>Marjo</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Schulman</surname><given-names>Alan H.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Schulman</surname><given-names>Leif</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Strona</surname><given-names>Giovanni</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Vanhatalo</surname><given-names>Jarno</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Understanding and applying biological resilience, from genes to ecosystems</article-title>
      <source>npj Biodiversity</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer Science; Business Media LLC</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2023-08">2023</year><month>08</month>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s44185-023-00022-6</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-WestEberhard2003">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>West-Eberhard</surname><given-names>Mary Jane</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Developmental plasticity and evolution</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
      <isbn>0195122356</isbn>
      <uri>https://www.amazon.com/Developmental-Plasticity-Evolution-Mary-West-Eberhard/dp/0195122356?SubscriptionId=0JYN1NVW651KCA56C102&amp;tag=techkie-20&amp;linkCode=xm2&amp;camp=2025&amp;creative=165953&amp;creativeASIN=0195122356</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-WestEberhard2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>West-Eberhard</surname><given-names>Mary Jane</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Modularity as a universal emergent property of biological traits</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Experimental Zoology Part B: Molecular and Developmental Evolution</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-11">2019</year><month>11</month>
      <volume>332</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jez.b.22913</pub-id>
      <fpage>356</fpage>
      <lpage>364</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Badyaev2005">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Badyaev</surname><given-names>Alexander V.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Role of stress in evolution</article-title>
      <source>Variation: A central topic in biology</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Hallgrímsson</surname><given-names>Benedikt</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Brian K.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year>
      <isbn>978-0-12-088777-4</isbn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/b978-012088777-4/50015-6</pub-id>
      <fpage>277</fpage>
      <lpage>302</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Badyaev2015">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Badyaev</surname><given-names>Alexander V.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>Erin S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Belloni</surname><given-names>Virginia</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Tradeoff between robustness and elaboration in carotenoid networks produces cycles of avian color diversification</article-title>
      <source>Biology Direct</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer Science; Business Media LLC</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2015-08">2015</year><month>08</month>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13062-015-0073-6</pub-id>
      <fpage>45</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Capra2014">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Capra</surname><given-names>Fritjof</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Luisi</surname><given-names>Pier Luigi</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The systems view of life</source>
      <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
      <isbn>1316616436</isbn>
      <uri>https://www.ebook.de/de/product/26316581/fritjof_capra_pier_luigi_luisi_the_systems_view_of_life.html</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Alscher1990">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Alscher</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Cumming</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Stress responses in plants: Adaptation and acclimation mechanisms</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley-Liss</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <fpage>407</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Darwin1859">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Darwin</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>On the origin of species by means of natural selection</source>
      <publisher-name>John Murray</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1859">1859</year>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2021-12-24">2021</year><month>12</month><day>24</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>https://archive.org/details/onoriginofspecie1859darw</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-GodfreySmith2009">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Godfrey-Smith</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Darwinian populations and natural selection</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Oxford New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
      <isbn>9780199596270</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Jansen2017">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>Marcel A. K.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Potters</surname><given-names>Geert</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Strees: The way of life</article-title>
      <source>Plant stress physiology</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Shabala</surname><given-names>Segei</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>CABI</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Wallingford</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      <edition>2</edition>
      <isbn>978 1 78064 729 6</isbn>
      <fpage>xi</fpage>
      <lpage>xiv</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Levine1985">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>Seymour</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A definition of stress?</article-title>
      <source>Animal stress</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1985">1985</year>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4614-7544-6_4</pub-id>
      <fpage>51</fpage>
      <lpage>69</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Grubb1992">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Grubb</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A positive distrust in simplicity — lessons from plant defences and from competition among plants and among animals</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Ecology</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year>
      <volume>80</volume>
      <fpage>585</fpage>
      <lpage>610</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Bidwell1979">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bidwell</surname><given-names>Roger G. S.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant physiology</source>
      <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1979">1979</year>
      <edition>2</edition>
      <isbn>0023094303</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Levitt1980">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>Jacob</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Responses of plants to environmental stresses</source>
      <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1980">1980</year>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <edition>2. ed.</edition>
      <isbn>0124455026</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Grime1979">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Grime</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant strategies and vegetation processes</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1979">1979</year>
      <isbn>9780471996927</isbn>
      <uri>https://books.google.fi/books?id=75nwAAAAMAAJ</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Grime1981">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Grime</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Plant strategies in shade</article-title>
      <source>Plants and the daylight spectrum</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1981">1981</year>
      <fpage>159</fpage>
      <lpage>186</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Chapin1987">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Chapin</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Waring</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Plant responses to multiple environmental factors</article-title>
      <source>BioScience</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1987-01">1987</year><month>01</month>
      <volume>37</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1310177</pub-id>
      <fpage>49</fpage>
      <lpage>57</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Packham1992">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Packham</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>D. J. L.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Hilton</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Stuttard</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Functional ecology of woodlands and forests</source>
      <publisher-name>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year>
      <fpage>407</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Lichtenthaler1998">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Lichtenthaler</surname><given-names>Hartmut K.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The stress concept in plants: An introduction</article-title>
      <source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1998-06">1998</year><month>06</month>
      <volume>851</volume>
      <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-6632.1998.tb08993.x</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.1998.tb08993.x</pub-id>
      <fpage>187</fpage>
      <lpage>198</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Koerner2003">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Körner</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Limitation and stress  always or never ?</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Vegetation Science</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1658/1100-9233(2003)014[0141:lasaon]2.0.co;2</pub-id>
      <fpage>141</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Gutschick2003">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Gutschick</surname><given-names>Vincent P</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>BassiriRad</surname><given-names>Hormoz</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Extreme events as shaping physiology, ecology, and evolution of plants: Toward a unified definition and evaluation of their consequences</article-title>
      <source>New Phytologist</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley Online Library</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
      <volume>160</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1469-8137.2003.00866.x</pub-id>
      <fpage>21</fpage>
      <lpage>42</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Goldberg1997">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Novoplansky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>On the relative importance of competition in unproductive environments</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Ecology</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year>
      <volume>85</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2960565</pub-id>
      <fpage>409</fpage>
      <lpage>418</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-MartinezGhersa2000">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Martı'nez-Ghersa</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ghersa</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Satorre</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Coevolution of agricultural systems and their weed companions: Implications for research</article-title>
      <source>Field Crops Research</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year>
      <volume>67</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-4290(00)00092-7</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Denison2012">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Denison</surname><given-names>R Ford</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Darwinian agriculture: How understanding evolution can improve agriculture</source>
      <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
      <isbn>9781400842810</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Aphalo1995">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Aphalo</surname><given-names>Pedro J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ballaré</surname><given-names>Carlos L.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>On the importance of information-acquiring systems in plant-plant interactions</article-title>
      <source>Functional Ecology</source>
      <publisher-loc>reprint</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <uri>http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0269-8463%28199502%299%3A1%3C5%3AOTIOIS%3E2.0.CO%3B2-A</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2390084</pub-id>
      <fpage>5</fpage>
      <lpage>14</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Callaway2002">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The detection of neighbors by plants</article-title>
      <source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source>
      <publisher-loc>reprint pedro (7124)</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <fpage>104</fpage>
      <lpage>105</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Schulze2005">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>Ernst-Detlef</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>Erwin</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Müller-Hohenstein</surname><given-names>Klaus</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant ecology</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Book Pedro Viikki Science Library</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2005-05">2005</year><month>05</month>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <isbn>354020833X</isbn>
      <fpage>700</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Kranner2010">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Kranner</surname><given-names>Ilse</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Minibayeva</surname><given-names>Farida V.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>Richard P.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Seal</surname><given-names>Charlotte E.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>What is stress? Concepts, definitions and applications in seed science</article-title>
      <source>New Phytologist</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2010-09">2010</year><month>09</month>
      <volume>188</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03461.x</pub-id>
      <fpage>655</fpage>
      <lpage>673</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Taiz2015">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Taiz</surname><given-names>Lincoln</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Zeiger</surname><given-names>Eduardo</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Moller</surname><given-names>Ian M.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>Angus</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant physiology and development</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Zeiger</surname><given-names>Eduardo</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Møller</surname><given-names>Ian Max</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>Angus</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sinauer Assoc.</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sunderland, Mass.</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
      <edition>6</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-60535-255-8</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Fisher1958">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>Ronald A.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Genetical theory of natural selection</source>
      <publisher-name>Dover Publications Inc.</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1958">1958</year>
      <isbn>9780486604664</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Smith1981">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Light quality as an ecological factor</article-title>
      <source>Plants and their atmospheric environment, 21st symposium of the british ecological society</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Blackwell Scientific Publications</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1981">1981</year>
      <fpage>93</fpage>
      <lpage>110</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Ballare1990">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Ballaré</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Scopel</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Far-red radiation reflected from adjacent leaves: An early signal of competition in plant canopies</article-title>
      <source>Science</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year>
      <volume>247</volume>
      <issue>4940</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.247.4940.329</pub-id>
      <fpage>329</fpage>
      <lpage>332</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Aphalo2022">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Aphalo</surname><given-names>Pedro J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>Victor O.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Explaining preemptive acclimation by linking information to plant phenotype</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
      <volume>73</volume>
      <issue>15</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erab537</pub-id>
      <fpage>5213</fpage>
      <lpage>5234</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Novoplansky2016">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Novoplansky</surname><given-names>Ariel</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Future perception in plants</article-title>
      <source>Anticipation across disciplines</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Nadin</surname><given-names>Mihai</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
      <isbn>9783319225999</isbn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-22599-9_5</pub-id>
      <fpage>57</fpage>
      <lpage>70</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Falik2024">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Falik</surname><given-names>Omer</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mauda</surname><given-names>Shachar</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Novoplansky</surname><given-names>Ariel</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The ecological implications of interplant drought cuing</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Ecology</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year>
      <volume>111</volume>
      <issn>1365-2745</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2745.13991</pub-id>
      <fpage>23</fpage>
      <lpage>32</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Novoplansky1990">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Novoplansky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>How portulaca seedlings avoid their neighbors</article-title>
      <source>Oecologia</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year>
      <volume>82</volume>
      <uri>http://www.springerlink.com/content/r2g5rt886884h188/?p=544f03666dfc45b787e01d464fe71616&amp;pi=10</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00319791</pub-id>
      <fpage>490</fpage>
      <lpage>493</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Boccalandro2003">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Boccalandro</surname><given-names>Hernán E</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ploschuk</surname><given-names>Edmundo L</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>Marcelo J</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>Rodolfo A</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Gatz</surname><given-names>Christiane</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>Jorge J</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Increased phytochrome b alleviates density effects on tuber yield of field potato crops.</article-title>
      <source>Plant Physiology</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003-12">2003</year><month>12</month>
      <volume>133</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.029579</pub-id>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14605224</pub-id>
      <fpage>1539</fpage>
      <lpage>1546</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Trewavas2014">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Trewavas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant behaviour and intelligence</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
      <isbn>9780199539543</isbn>
      <uri>https://books.google.fi/books?id=6Pk5BAAAQBAJ</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Sadras2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>Victor O.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Agricultural technology is unavoidable, directional, combinatory, disruptive, unpredictable and has unintended consequences</article-title>
      <source>Outlook on Agriculture</source>
      <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <volume>49</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0030727020960493</pub-id>
      <fpage>003072702096049</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Bonduriansky2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bonduriansky</surname><given-names>Russell</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>Troy</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Extended heredity: A new understanding of inheritance and evolution</source>
      <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <isbn>9780691204147</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Mindell2024">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Mindell</surname><given-names>David P.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The network of life: A new view of evolution</source>
      <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year>
      <isbn>9780691228761</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Shemesh2013">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Shemesh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Novoplansky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Branching the risks: Architectural plasticity and bet-hedging in mediterranean annuals</article-title>
      <source>Plant biology (Stuttgart, Germany)</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1438-8677.2012.00705.x</pub-id>
      <fpage>1001</fpage>
      <lpage>1012</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Bradshaw1965">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Evolutionary significance of phenotypic plasticity in plants</article-title>
      <source>Advances in genetics</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1965">1965</year>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0065-2660(08)60048-6</pub-id>
      <fpage>115</fpage>
      <lpage>155</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Reymond2003">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>Matthieu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>Bertrand</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>Agnès</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Charcosset</surname><given-names>Alain</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Tardieu</surname><given-names>François</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Combining quantitative trait loci analysis and an ecophysiological model to analyze the genetic variability of the responses of maize leaf growth to temperature and water deficit</article-title>
      <source>Plant Physiology</source>
      <publisher-name>Am Soc Plant Biol</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
      <volume>131</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.013839</pub-id>
      <fpage>664</fpage>
      <lpage>675</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Agren2012">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Ågren</surname><given-names>Göran I.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Weih</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Plant stoichiometry at different scales: Element concentration patterns reflect environment more than genotype</article-title>
      <source>New Phytologist</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2012-04">2012</year><month>04</month>
      <volume>194</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2012.04114.x</pub-id>
      <fpage>944</fpage>
      <lpage>952</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Sinclair2012">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>Thomas R.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Rufty</surname><given-names>Thomas W.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Nitrogen and water resources commonly limit crop yield increases, not necessarily plant genetics</article-title>
      <source>Global Food Security</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2012-12">2012</year><month>12</month>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gfs.2012.07.001</pub-id>
      <fpage>94</fpage>
      <lpage>98</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Bloom1985">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>A J</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Chapin</surname><given-names>F S</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>H A</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Resource limitation in plants-an economic analogy</article-title>
      <source>Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1985">1985</year>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.es.16.110185.002051</pub-id>
      <fpage>363</fpage>
      <lpage>392</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Karban2015">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Karban</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant sensing and communication</source>
      <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
      <isbn>022626470X</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Ovaska1993">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Ovaska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ruuska</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Rintamaki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Vapaavuori</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Combined effects of partial defoliation and nutrient availability on cloned betula pendula saplings .2. Changes in net photosynthesis and related biochemical properties</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year>
      <volume>44</volume>
      <issue>265</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/44.8.1395</pub-id>
      <fpage>1395</fpage>
      <lpage>1402</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Efron2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Efron</surname><given-names>Bradley</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Prediction, estimation, and attribution</article-title>
      <source>Journal of the American Statistical Association</source>
      <publisher-name>Informa UK Limited</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020-04">2020</year><month>04</month>
      <volume>115</volume>
      <issue>530</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01621459.2020.1762613</pub-id>
      <fpage>636</fpage>
      <lpage>655</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Noble2017">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>Denis</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Evolution viewed from physics, physiology and medicine</article-title>
      <source>Interface Focus</source>
      <publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017-08">2017</year><month>08</month>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsfs.2016.0159</pub-id>
      <fpage>20160159</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Noble2012">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>Denis</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A theory of biological relativity: No privileged level of causation</article-title>
      <source>Interface Focus</source>
      <publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2012-11">2012</year><month>11</month>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsfs.2011.0067</pub-id>
      <fpage>55</fpage>
      <lpage>64</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Passioura2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Passioura</surname><given-names>John B.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Translational research in agriculture. Can we do it better?</article-title>
      <source>Crop and Pasture Science</source>
      <publisher-name>CSIRO Publishing</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <volume>71</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/cp20066</pub-id>
      <fpage>517</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Rai2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>Neha</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>Luis O.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Aphalo</surname><given-names>Pedro J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Perception of solar UV radiation by plants: Photoreceptors and mechanisms</article-title>
      <source>Plant Physiology</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021-04">2021</year><month>04</month>
      <volume>186</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/plphys/kiab162</pub-id>
      <fpage>1382</fpage>
      <lpage>1396</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Podolec2021a">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Podolec</surname><given-names>Roman</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Demarsy</surname><given-names>Emilie</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ulm</surname><given-names>Roman</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Perception and signaling of ultraviolet-b radiation in plants</article-title>
      <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <volume>72</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <uri>https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-arplant-050718-095946</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-050718-095946</pub-id>
      <fpage>793</fpage>
      <lpage>822</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Sellaro2024">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Sellaro</surname><given-names>Romina</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>Maxime</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Aphalo</surname><given-names>Pedro J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>Jorge J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Making the most of canopy light: Shade avoidance under a fluctuating spectrum and irradiance</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Panigrahy</surname><given-names>Madhusmita</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2024-08">2024</year><month>08</month>
      <issn>1460-2431</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erae334</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Casal2018">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>Jorge J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Qüesta</surname><given-names>Julia I.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Light and temperature cues: Multitasking receptors and transcriptional integrators</article-title>
      <source>New Phytologist</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2018-11">2018</year><month>11</month>
      <volume>217</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14890</pub-id>
      <fpage>1029</fpage>
      <lpage>1034</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Meadows2015">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Meadows</surname><given-names>Donella</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Thinking in systems</source>
      <publisher-name>Chelsea Green Publishing Co</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2015-09-14">2015</year><month>09</month><day>14</day>
      <isbn>1603580557</isbn>
      <uri>https://www.ebook.de/de/product/7353874/donella_meadows_thinking_in_systems.html</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Shevela2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Shevela</surname><given-names>Dmitry</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Björn</surname><given-names>Lars Olof</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Govindjee</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Photosynthesis: Solar energy for life</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>null</surname></name>
        <name><surname>Björn</surname><given-names>Lars Olof</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>World Scientific Publishing Co Pte Ltd</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
      <isbn>9789813223103</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Yan2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Stoddard</surname><given-names>Frederick L.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Neugart</surname><given-names>Susanne</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Oravec</surname><given-names>Michal</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>Otmar</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>Victor O.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Aphalo</surname><given-names>Pedro J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The transgenerational effects of solar short-UV radiation differed in two accessions of vicia faba l. From contrasting UV environments</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Plant Physiology</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <volume>248</volume>
      <issn>0176-1617</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2020.153145</pub-id>
      <fpage>153145</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Novoplansky2009">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Novoplansky</surname><given-names>Ariel</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Picking battles wisely: Plant behaviour under competition</article-title>
      <source>Plant Cell and Environment</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
      <volume>32</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <issn>0140-7791</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2009.01979.x</pub-id>
      <fpage>726</fpage>
      <lpage>741</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Chapin1987">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Chapin</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Waring</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Plant responses to multiple environmental factors</article-title>
      <source>BioScience</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1987-01">1987</year><month>01</month>
      <volume>37</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1310177</pub-id>
      <fpage>49</fpage>
      <lpage>57</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Kauffman2023">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>Stuart A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Roli</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A third transition in science?</article-title>
      <source>Interface Focus</source>
      <publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2023-04">2023</year><month>04</month>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <issn>2042-8901</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsfs.2022.0063</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Reynolds2022">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>Andrew S.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Understanding metaphors in the life sciences</source>
      <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2022-04">2022</year><month>04</month>
      <isbn>9781108940498</isbn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/9781108938778</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Wimsatt1976">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wimsatt</surname><given-names>William C.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Reductionism, levels of organization, and the mind-body problem</article-title>
      <source>Consciousness and the brain</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1976">1976</year>
      <isbn>9781468421965</isbn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4684-2196-5_9</pub-id>
      <fpage>205</fpage>
      <lpage>267</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Wimsatt1994">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wimsatt</surname><given-names>William C.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The ontology of complex systems: Levels of organization, perspectives, and causal thickets</article-title>
      <source>Canadian Journal of Philosophy Supplementary Volume</source>
      <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press (CUP)</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year>
      <volume>20</volume>
      <issn>2633-0490</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00455091.1994.10717400</pub-id>
      <fpage>207</fpage>
      <lpage>274</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Mooney1991">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Winner</surname><given-names>William E.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Response of plants to multiple stresses</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Winner</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Pell</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1991">1991</year>
      <isbn>9780125053556</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Bloom1985">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Chapin</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Resource limitation in plants: An economic analogy</article-title>
      <source>Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1985">1985</year>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.es.16.110185.002051</pub-id>
      <fpage>363</fpage>
      <lpage>392</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Aarssen2015">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Aarssen</surname><given-names>Lonnie W.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Body size and fitness in plants: Revisiting the selection consequences of competition</article-title>
      <source>Perspectives in Plant Ecology, Evolution and Systematics</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2015-05">2015</year><month>05</month>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <issn>1433-8319</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ppees.2015.02.004</pub-id>
      <fpage>236</fpage>
      <lpage>242</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Abbo2022">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Abbo</surname><given-names>Shahal</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Gopher</surname><given-names>Avi</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bar-Gal</surname><given-names>Gila Kahila</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant domestication and the origins of agriculture in the ancient near east</source>
      <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2022-03">2022</year><month>03</month>
      <isbn>9781108737708</isbn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/9781108642491</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Cossani2018">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Cossani</surname><given-names>Cesar Mariano</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>Victor O.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Water–nitrogen colimitation in grain crops</article-title>
      <source>Advances in agronomy</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
      <issn>0065-2113</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.agron.2018.02.004</pub-id>
      <fpage>231</fpage>
      <lpage>274</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Elser2007">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Elser</surname><given-names>James J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bracken</surname><given-names>Matthew E. S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>Elsa E.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Gruner</surname><given-names>Daniel S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Harpole</surname><given-names>W. Stanley</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Hillebrand</surname><given-names>Helmut</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ngai</surname><given-names>Jacqueline T.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Seabloom</surname><given-names>Eric W.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Shurin</surname><given-names>Jonathan B.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Jennifer E.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Global analysis of nitrogen and phosphorus limitation of primary producers in freshwater, marine and terrestrial ecosystems</article-title>
      <source>Ecology Letters</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2007-10">2007</year><month>10</month>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <issn>1461-0248</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2007.01113.x</pub-id>
      <fpage>1135</fpage>
      <lpage>1142</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Selye1936">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Selye</surname><given-names>Hans</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A syndrome produced by diverse nocuous agents</article-title>
      <source>Nature</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer Science; Business Media LLC</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1936-07">1936</year><month>07</month>
      <volume>138</volume>
      <issue>3479</issue>
      <issn>1476-4687</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/138032a0</pub-id>
      <fpage>32</fpage>
      <lpage>32</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Harris1970">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>Dorothy V.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>On the brink of catastrophe</article-title>
      <source>Quest</source>
      <publisher-name>Informa UK Limited</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1970-01">1970</year><month>01</month>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <issn>1543-2750</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00336297.1970.10519674</pub-id>
      <fpage>33</fpage>
      <lpage>40</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Zarka2022">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Zarka</surname><given-names>Jens</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>De Wint</surname><given-names>Frederik C.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>De Bruyn</surname><given-names>Luc</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bonte</surname><given-names>Dries</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Parmentier</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Dissecting the costs of a facultative symbiosis in an isopod living with ants</article-title>
      <source>Oecologia</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer Science; Business Media LLC</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2022-05">2022</year><month>05</month>
      <volume>199</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <issn>1432-1939</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-022-05186-9</pub-id>
      <fpage>355</fpage>
      <lpage>366</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Gu2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Tingting</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Shanshan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Lu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Yunfei</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Yuan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Zhou</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Predator-induced allometric changes in the tail spine length ofDaphnia: A distinct resource allocation strategy</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Plankton Research</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021-09">2021</year><month>09</month>
      <volume>43</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <issn>1464-3774</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/plankt/fbab063</pub-id>
      <fpage>884</fpage>
      <lpage>893</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Guarin2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Guarin</surname><given-names>Jose Rafael</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kassie</surname><given-names>Belay</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mashaheet</surname><given-names>Alsayed M.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Burkey</surname><given-names>Kent</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Asseng</surname><given-names>Senthold</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Modeling the effects of tropospheric ozone on wheat growth and yield</article-title>
      <source>European Journal of Agronomy</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-04">2019</year><month>04</month>
      <volume>105</volume>
      <issn>1161-0301</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eja.2019.02.004</pub-id>
      <fpage>13</fpage>
      <lpage>23</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Harpole2011">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Harpole</surname><given-names>W. Stanley</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ngai</surname><given-names>Jacqueline T.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>Elsa E.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Seabloom</surname><given-names>Eric W.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Borer</surname><given-names>Elizabeth T.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bracken</surname><given-names>Matthew E. S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Elser</surname><given-names>James J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Gruner</surname><given-names>Daniel S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Hillebrand</surname><given-names>Helmut</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Shurin</surname><given-names>Jonathan B.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Jennifer E.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Nutrient co‐limitation of primary producer communities</article-title>
      <source>Ecology Letters</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2011-07">2011</year><month>07</month>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <issn>1461-0248</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2011.01651.x</pub-id>
      <fpage>852</fpage>
      <lpage>862</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Hu2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Changlu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>Victor O.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Guoyan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Runze</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Xueyun</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Shulan</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Root pruning enhances wheat yield, harvest index and water-use efficiency in semiarid area</article-title>
      <source>Field Crops Research</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-01">2019</year><month>01</month>
      <volume>230</volume>
      <issn>0378-4290</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fcr.2018.10.013</pub-id>
      <fpage>62</fpage>
      <lpage>71</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Khan2022">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Faisal</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Yupeng</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Palta</surname><given-names>Jairo A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Yinglong</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sadras</surname><given-names>Victor O.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Siddique</surname><given-names>Kadambot H. M.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Selection for yield over five decades favored anisohydric and phenological adaptations to early-season drought in australian wheat</article-title>
      <source>Plant and Soil</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2022-07-01">2022</year><month>07</month><day>01</day>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-10-14">2024</year><month>10</month><day>14</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>476</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <issn>1573-5036</issn>
      <uri>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11104-022-05543-w</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-022-05543-w</pub-id>
      <fpage>511</fpage>
      <lpage>526</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Kho2000">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Kho</surname><given-names>Ramun M.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>On crop production and the balance of available resources</article-title>
      <source>Agriculture, Ecosystems &amp;amp; Environment</source>
      <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2000-08">2000</year><month>08</month>
      <volume>80</volume>
      <issue>1–2</issue>
      <issn>0167-8809</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0167-8809(00)00135-3</pub-id>
      <fpage>71</fpage>
      <lpage>85</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Lass2003">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Lass</surname><given-names>Sandra</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Spaak</surname><given-names>Piet</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Chemically induced anti-predator defences in plankton: A review</article-title>
      <source>Hydrobiologia</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer Science; Business Media LLC</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003-01">2003</year><month>01</month>
      <volume>491</volume>
      <issue>1–3</issue>
      <issn>0018-8158</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/a:1024487804497</pub-id>
      <fpage>221</fpage>
      <lpage>239</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Richards1981a">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Passioura</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Seminal root morphology and water use of wheat II. Genetic variation</article-title>
      <source>Crop Science</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1981-03">1981</year><month>03</month>
      <volume>21</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <issn>1435-0653</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1981.0011183x002100020012x</pub-id>
      <fpage>253</fpage>
      <lpage>255</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Richards1989">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Passioura</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A breeding program to reduce the diameter of the major xylem vessel in the seminal roots of wheat and its effect on grain yield in rain-fed environments</article-title>
      <source>Australian Journal of Agricultural Research</source>
      <publisher-name>CSIRO Publishing</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1989">1989</year>
      <volume>40</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <issn>0004-9409</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/ar9890943</pub-id>
      <fpage>943</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-SantosDiaz2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Santos-Díaz</surname><given-names>María del Socorro</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Camarena-Rangel</surname><given-names>Nancy Gabriela</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Cacti for production of metabolites: Current state and perspectives</article-title>
      <source>Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer Science; Business Media LLC</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-09">2019</year><month>09</month>
      <volume>103</volume>
      <issue>21–22</issue>
      <issn>1432-0614</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-019-10125-5</pub-id>
      <fpage>8657</fpage>
      <lpage>8667</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Schoppach2017">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Schoppach</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sadok</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Transpiration sensitivity to evaporative demand across 120 years of breeding of australian wheat cultivars</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Agronomy and Crop Science</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      <volume>203</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <issn>1439-037X</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jac.12193</pub-id>
      <fpage>219</fpage>
      <lpage>226</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Woltereck1909">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Woltereck</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Weitere experimentelle untersuchungen über artveränderung, speziell über das wesen quantitativer artunterschiede bei daphniden</article-title>
      <source>Verhandlungen der Deutschen Zoologischen Gesellschaft</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1909">1909</year>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <fpage>110</fpage>
      <lpage>172</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Chapin2011">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Chapin</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Matson</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Vitousek</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Principles of terrestrial ecosystem ecology</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2011-09">2011</year><month>09</month>
      <edition>2nd ed. 2012</edition>
      <isbn>144199503X</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Wheeler1975">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>Harry</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Plant pathogenesis</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Berlin New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1975">1975</year>
      <isbn>3540073582</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
</ref-list>
</back>


</article>